Now useEffect can be tricky to use though because right now, it runs all the time,
it combines componentDidMount and componentDidUpdate.
Now what if we were to send an HTTP request here but we only want to do that when the component is rendered
for the first time and not for every re-render cycle,
what would we do then? To highlight this problem,
let's add a set timeout call here and maybe add a timeout of one second and after one second, this function will
execute and I'm just doing this to kind of fake an HTTP request here.
This is of course no HTTP request but it takes some time to finish and then does something and what it
does here is it should throw an alert, saved data to cloud.
Now we might be fine with that alert showing when we really saved something to the cloud,
so when this component loaded for example or maybe we fetched data from the cloud, doesn't matter. So therefore,
we would be fine with seeing this if we reload,
OK
and now I click here and yes, I get this again,
thank you. And I click here and I want to delete something and I get this again.
Now this might not be what I want,
how can I control when this actually executes?
For example let's say this should only execute because it is saving data to the cloud
when our persons changed but not on any other condition.
Well for that, you can add a second argument here to useEffect, that second argument is an array where
you simply point at all the variables or all the data that actually are used in your effect. Right now
React is not smart enough to find out on its own and actually here it couldn't because we're not using
any data in here
but if we know, we only want to run this code when our persons changed,
well then you simply add props persons here.
Now by the way if you have different effects that depend on different data, you can use useEffect more
than once,
that is absolutely fine,
you can have as many useEffect setups here or functions as you want.
So now this effect should only execute when our persons changed. So if I reload this, it runs initially
and if I toggle my persons
now, there is no alert because persons didn't change.
If I type an I, I of course get it again because that changes my persons.
If I toggle persons, it does not come again because that didn't change my persons.
So that is already an improvement, it allows us to control when this executes which is very useful.
What if we now only want to execute this when the component renders the first time?
Well for this, there is a little shortcut so to say, you can pass an empty array,
you have to pass an array, that's important but it's empty.
This tells React this effect has no dependencies and it should rerun whenever one of the dependencies
changes.
Now if you have no dependencies, they can never change and therefore this can never rerun, it will run
for the first time,
that is the default but it will never run again.
So now therefore, we get this initially but thereafter we can do whatever we want
and this does not come back.
So if you just need componentDidMount, you would use useEffect with an empty array passed as a second
argument to the useEffect function. If you have a dependency on a certain field, you do what we did before,
you pass that field in here
and of course, you can have multiple fields you will depend on.