We had a look at the useEffect hook here and I just came up with one interesting change to it here actually.
Now we do have our app here that when it reloads, it gives us this alert, right.
Now what if I remove the cockpit,
the alert still shows.
Now I explained how we could do cleanup work here,
why don't we just do it?
We have that timer which I certainly want to remove if this cockpit component here unmounts and this
code here runs when it unmounts
because of that second argument where we have an empty array which ensures that this code executes only
when a component is mounted and rendered for the first time and when it then is unmounted.
So let's actually store our timer here in a constant, timer and let's clear this timeout when we
umount.
So here I can call clear timeout and pass timer,
so this constant here. And with that if I save this and this app reloads, now if I remove this, we never see
the alert because the timer never goes off because I clean it up when this cockpit is unmounted
and if I do that before the alert shows, so before the timer finished, then it's simply canceled
and of course if I don't do that, then we see the alert.
So that was just a tiny variation which I came up with after this initial recording which I of course
didn't want to hide from you.
Now I'll remove it here because I don't have it in the code for the next lectures but still, this is a great
example for how you can do cleanup work in useEffect.