Before we have a look at the internal re-rendering process, let's have a look at how we can optimize performance
with functional components though because shouldComponentUpdate is a great tool but it's only available
in class-based components.
Now what about functional components, what can we do there,
what about the cockpit component?
Because with the paint flashing, we see that and I will disable this now, we see that of course the cockpit
is never touched when I type here
but still we can tell that it executed its code.
So how can we prevent this if nothing about the cockpit changed?
And for that, we first of all have to look at the cockpit and we see that the only thing that the cockpit
uses internally and that therefore should trigger a re-rendering of that cockpit are the persons length here
and then also this title.
The names of the persons and so on are totally irrelevant.
So what can you do now to prevent this unnecessary re-rendering? React
also has a tool for functional components. You can wrap your export, so your entire component here in
the cockpit.js file with React memo. This basically uses memoization which is a technique where React
will memoize,
so basically store a snapshot of this component and only if its input changes, it will re-render it
and otherwise if its inputs do not change and some parent component wants to update this cockpit component,
React will give back that stored component. So therefore now initially this of course runs because there
is no stored data and here it actually runs again, now why is that? Because in the cockpit component, it only
re-renders when its props change but of course one of the props we depend on is the persons.
We only use the length but that is not something React picks up here. To fix that, we can optimize the
way we pass data into our cockpit though. Here on cockpit instead of passing in the persons, we can pass
in the persons length let's say which is this state persons length.
So instead of determining the length inside of the cockpit, we do it outside of the cockpit
now and we only pass in persons length. This of course will now only change if the persons length here
changes.
So now back in the cockpit.js file where I used props persons.length,
I use props persons length but this is now a separate property,
there is no dot in between, I'm not accessing a length property here,
this is a new prop I get. Now with that, we made that calculation or we outsourced that calculation that
used the complete persons array which of course changes with every keystroke, we outsourced this into app.js
and now we only get data that does not change with every keystroke and therefore now if I clear this,
if I type here, we see nothing about cockpit.js being executed here.
This will only happen once we do something that does affect the cockpit,
so then you see that run but you don't see any cockpit output for changes that do not relate to it. So
React memo is a great way of also getting optimization for your functional components and therefore
it is a good idea to wrap functional components that might not need to update with every change in the
parent component with it.