Now with the React memo and shouldComponentUpdate, it would be kind of logical to basically add either
of the two to any component you're creating,
every functional component could be wrapped with React memo and every class-based component could implement
shouldComponentUpdate.
Is that wise?
Now this might sound like a good idea
but it actually isn't.
You will have components that will basically always update when their parent updates.
In such cases where you depend on some input from your parent component, that is about the only data
your parent component manages and therefore when your parent component updates,
you will also have to update because then that data changed. In such cases if you implement shouldComponentUpdate
or React memo,
then these functions will run and will check whether the input changed and they will find out
yes it changed like it always does and they will allow you to re-render.
So all good, right?
You didn't stop anything from happening. Well but you executed this unnecessary code.
This check here of course doesn't come for free.
It's not a super performance heavy check but still, it is code that executes
and if you wrap all your components with such checks and let's say 60% of your components actually
always need to update when their parent updates,
well if you then wrapped all your components with these extra checks, then you're running unnecessary
checks on 60% of your component codebase and that is not really something you want to do. So
you should evaluate this carefully,
is this component part of a parent component that could change related to something that does not affect
me at all, as it is the case here where the persons component is certainly not interested in changes
related to the cockpit,
well then you should implement your check here.
Otherwise if you're pretty sure that in all or almost all cases where your parent updates, you will need
to update too,
then you should not add shouldComponentUpdate or React memo because you will just execute some extra
logic that makes no sense and actually just slows down the application a tiny bit.