There is something I want to add to the lectures where we worked with shouldComponentUpdate.
If you are having a class-based component, so a component created with the class keyword extending component,
where you implement shouldComponentUpdate,
if you implement a check where you simply want to compare all props that matter to a component for difference,
then there is an easier way of writing that component.
Let me demonstrate this at the example of the persons component. There
I'm currently checking whether persons changed.
Now let's see which props we're using in persons.
We're not just using person data, so we're not just using persons from our props,
we also have the changed function which we trigger and the clicked function.
Now these are functions not data we output, yet
if such a function reference would change, if we somehow get a new function reference from outside, then
this component will need to know about that and it should update appropriately.
Therefore you could argue that we want to update this if check here to check whether persons is different
or if next props changed is different to this props changed, referring to that changed function or
if next props clicked,
so with that I mean this property here, is different to our current
clicked value, so if it's not equal to this props clicked. So I now added these new two if checks and if any
of them basically returns true,
so if something changed here, then we will continue with the update,
if neither persons nor changed nor clicked were changed, we return false and we don't continue. Now with
that if I save that, if I toggle my persons here and I then remove the cockpit, you see that in our persons,
we still stop at shouldComponentUpdate because nothing changed about that,
if I type here however, we do continue with the update, so that works as before.
Now if you have such a scenario where you check all the props of a given component for changes, which
is not that uncommon of course because typically you want to make sure that no props of this component
changed and you're not just interested in one or two of the properties you are getting,
so if you are checking all properties, then you can also not use shouldComponentUpdate and therefore
I'll comment this out but instead extend a different type of component,
you can extend a pure component. So you can then simply extend pure component here and what pure component
does is it works just as before, I can type here and you see the persons update lifecycle runs
but if I remove the cockpit, we don't execute any code from persons, not even shouldComponentUpdate
because I commented that out but also no other lifecycle hook because pure component in the end is
just a normal component that already implements shouldComponentUpdate with a complete props check,
so that checks for any changes in any prop of that component.
So if that is what you need, you can also just use pure component instead of manually implementing this
shouldComponentUpdate check.
The result will be the same, so you can do either of these but of course you can save some code if you
use pure component.