Over the last lectures, we had a lot of deep dives into how components work under the hood, how they are
created and updated and how you can control updates and hook
and with that, I don't mean React hooks but tap into different points during the update and creation
cycle to execute your own code, both in functional components with the use of fact hook and in class
based components with the different lifecycle hooks we implemented there.
Now there is more to React components that I want to cover and I want to dive into something you'll
see throughout this course,
I want to dive into that thing that I mentioned that you have to always return
just one JSX element inside of a component.
Now that JSX element can contain other JSX elements, like here in the person component but you must
only have one root JSX element, be that another component or a normal HTML element. So I'm
not allowed, for example, to have an adjacent div here.
So if I try to return this and of course it does not matter if that's a div or a h1 tag or anything
like that, then I get an error, adjacent
JSX elements must be wrapped in enclosing tag. So I'm basically not allowed to return adjacent
JSX elements like this on a root level,
so inside of that div, so these elements here, there it's okay that they're adjacent but the root element
I'm returning in this component or in any place where I need to return JSX has to be one single element
with as many children as you want.
Now this is not entirely true though because if you have a look at the persons component, there we actually
return an array of persons, right? So that's not one single element,
it's an array. Now technically, an array of course still is one object but with multiple elements in there
and indeed, React does allow us to return an array of adjacent elements as long as all the items in there
have a key and that key is required so that React can efficiently update and reorder these elements
as it might be required by your app.
So where can we see this in action?
Well let's go back to the person component,
so a single person
and there we have that div with our CSS class
and of course that div is theoretically something I want here,
I want to have that wrapping container which implies a style
but for now, let's temporarily remove it and therefore of course this is invalid because now we have
adjacent elements but let's now not return them like this but let's wrap them in square brackets.
So here, I will return my JSX elements in an array.
Now this might look strange but remember, JSX is just syntactic sugar for React create element,
so in the end we're just returning a couple of calls to React create element here or the results of
these calls to be precise.
Hence we need to separate these items with commas after each of them,
right?
So a comma after the paragraph, a comma after this paragraph and then well this is the last element.
So this is now an array of elements and if I now save that, actually if I click toggle persons, it works
but I'm getting a warning regarding that key and that is what I mentioned,
you should add a key here.
Well for that, we can simply add a key on these elements
and here we're not generating the key dynamically, we're not extracting a unique value from anywhere.
You can of course assign your own unique value like i1 for item 1 or whatever you want,
any identifier that you simply don't repeat,
that's the only important thing,
each key here should be unique in that array.
So now I have three different keys and that means that this now works without any issue, without any
warning and in exactly the same way as before it.
The only difference is the missing styling because that div we had around our elements,
that actually was not just there to have a root level element, it did provide some useful styling but
that is OK here because I want to show you this concept of adjacent elements because later in this course
and also in the course project of this course, we will actually have use cases and scenarios where we
want to have multiple top level elements sit next to each other and having to introduce an extra wrapping
div or a section just because React forces us when we don't technically need it from a HTML
or CSS point of view, that is a bit of redundancy that we don't want to add to our app and therefore
it's important to know that if you don't technically need a wrapping element for a styling or structural
reasons, then you can avoid it by using an array but this is not even the only way of doing it. You can
of course create such an array but it's a bit inconvenient, you have to wrap this in square brackets,
you have to assign the key and so on, so that is not really that great. How else could you do that besides
using an array?
Well this approach might look a bit hacky at first but it's perfectly fine and actually built into
React as you will learn. You can create a wrapping component that does not render any actual HTML
code but that simply is there to fulfill React's requirement of having a wrapping component. And for this,
I'll create a new folder which I'll name hoc which stands for a higher order component and we'll dive
deeper into higher order components in the next lectures.
They are basically components that wrap other components and in there,
I will create a new file which I will name aux.js for auxilliary and side note for Windows users, there
aux.js will not work,
so on Windows you should name this auxilliary.js simply because aux is a reserved word or
name on Windows systems, on Linux and Mac, this is no problem.
Now how does this aux component look like?
First of all, I import React from React, that is important and then I have my const which I'll name
aux which gets props and that's the interesting thing, will only return props children here. Children
is a special property that simply outputs whatever gets entered between the opening and closing tag
of this component.
So then I export my aux component here as the default
and now we can import this into the person component,
so let's import aux with a capital A from and now let's go all the way up to the higher order component
folder and import aux
and now we can use aux like a regular JSX element to wrap all the other JSX code here, simply like
this.
Now that might look very strange at first because of course the aux component doesn't do anything
but as you can see, it works, it renders our content.
It's basically an empty wrapper
using that special children property which React reserves for us,
so that really is a reserved property name,
that React reserves for us and children will always refer to the content between the opening and closing
tag of your component.
So in this case, children will refer to all this content and all the aux component
does is it outputs that content.
Now you might argue but isn't is a set of adjacent elements in this place then.
Well that is the hard thing to wrap your head around, it kind of is
you could say but actually, it isn't because the requirement of having this wrapping top level element
is a pure technical one from a Javascript point of view that you must only return one expression and
that is what we're doing here because you must never forget that these JSX elements are always
calls to React create element and in a return statement, you couldn't return multiple React create element
calls like this next to each other and therefore you can't
do this either for JSX code. But the moment you wrap this with one React create element call so to say, this
works and then here in the aux component, you're just returning an input,
so technically from a Javascript point of view, that is fine,
we're only returning one expression here. So it can be tricky to wrap your head around, it is a pure
Javascript thing here or it's actually the case in most programming languages.
You must only return one expression and here it's one expression now
and here, it's now one expression.
Now as a side note, in the aux component, we now don't even need the React import here because we're not
using any JSX in here,
so we're not implicitly using React create element and therefore this works even if you remove that
import.