I mentioned that the aux component is a so-called higher order component which is why it's placed in
the hoc folder and it's named higher order component because all it does essentially is it wraps
another component,
it does not contain its own logic, its own styling or add any structure to the
JSX code or to the real DOM that will be rendered,
it just wraps another component and then maybe adds some extra logic to it, though the aux component
here doesn't even add any logic,
it's just a technical wrapper.
Now another example for a higher order component that you could create would be a component that sets
up a div that contains a class or sets up a class, like here. In app.js,
we're using a div and we're assigning a class there
and of course there's nothing wrong with that.
We're doing the same in our person component or we did before we added aux, before we did that,
here we also had a div where we assigned that person class.
Now obviously, there is nothing wrong with just using a div with a class name but this serves as a good
example for a custom higher order component you could create that does more than the aux component, so this
is simply an example
now. I will create a new file in the hoc folder and I'll name it withClass.js, like this.
It's kind of a convention to name higher order components with a with at the beginning, though of course
ultimately it's up to you how you name your components.
Now how does the withClass component look like?
Well this now needs to import React from React because it will render some JSX and then I'll name
it withClass here and this will be a regular functional component getting props
and then in the end, we'll export withClass here so that we can use it in other files.
Now inside of the function body or of the return statement of this function body which I have here,
I will render a div with a class name of and now that's the fun part, props classes let's say and
you can name this here classes whatever you want,
this will be a property I expect to get on that higher order component. Between my opening and closing
tags of the div, I'll then return props children which again is the entire content between the opening
and closing tag of this withClass component when we're using it.
So this is now my higher order component, withClass, that simply does one thing,
it sets up a class on a div that wraps my component.
Now how would we use that?
Let's test it in app.js, there
I will import WithClass like this with a capital W from hoc withClass and now withClass can be
used instead of the div here, so let me replace div opening and closing with
withClass and instead of class name, I will simply pass classes because in withClass, I'm expecting
a class property.
Now if I do that as the app reloads, you see it looks exactly the same way as before.
So if we check our app.css file, the text is still aligned in the center,
so if it wouldn't work, all our text should be on the left and
of course if I inspect any of these items here, I can indeed see that we are applying the style here.
Now let me repeat, this is just an example here,
obviously there would be nothing wrong with sticking to a div but we'll introduce other higher order
components throughout the course where we for example add error handling that we can wrap around any
component that makes an HTTP request and all of a sudden, this becomes more useful.
The general concept is simply that you have a component that wraps other components that adds something
to it, that could be styling, that could be additional HTML structure around it or that could also
be some logic and we'll add that logic later once we added HTTP requests
as I said, to automatically handle HTTP errors.