So now with the higher order component created, let's maybe also use it in the person.js file for a
single person
where I also want to have a class around it, right?
I use my aux component here because I want to demonstrate the aux component but we actually have
some CSS class code set up that we could use here.
Now we can of course simply import withClass here from
the higher order component folder and then the withClass file and then we can use this higher order
component on the person component as well.
It's not limited to being used in one component only, you can bring it into any component that needs
the functionality
this higher order component adds and the functionality this higher order component adds is that it adds
a wrapping div with some CSS code.
So therefore, let's now use it here,
withClass and let's pass the person component as the first argument and the class I want to add is
classes.person, using the CSS modules and this person class here.
Now with that, with everything set up, that should bring back our styles for the persons.
So if we toggle them,
yes
the styling is back but the data is missing
and do you know what's wrong here?
The data is missing because what we're doing is we're taking our person component and right before we
export it, we pass it into the withClass function.
Now what does the withClass function do? The withClass function takes the component and outputs it
not before wrapping it into an extra div that adds the CSS class. The div doesn't really matter but
what is missing on the wrapped component which in the case of the person component being passed is just
our person component.
Well it's missing all its props,
I'm outputting wrapped components like this and I haven't set any props here.
Of course we could set name as a prop here but for one, this is now hardcoded and second, now every
component using that higher order component would receive Maximilian as we can see here and that is certainly
not what we want, even though it's a great name of course.
Well, we can pass props dynamically and that is a pretty powerful feature of Javascript and React.
We actually do accept our props here and this will be the props of our wrapped component because we
return this functional component in our higher order component,
so ultimately, this withClass finger returns the functional component that wraps our person component.
So we export whatever withClass returns, so we export this functional component returned by withClass and
therefore anyone importing from person component and using the export here as person, as we do it here
in the persons file,
this here refers just to the result of the withClass call.
So it refers to this functional component and therefore any props we pass to person here in the persons
component will end up in our withClass component here.
So props will actually be the right props and now we can use a JSX syntax that allows us to forward
props to the wrapped component.
Now what doesn't work is that we set props equal to props because React automatically takes all
the attributes you add to your JSX code and combines them in a props object.
So now props would not replace that props object but be added as a single property in the props passed
to the wrapped component.
But instead, you can use another syntax where you use curly braces and then a feature called the spread
operator where you spread the props you're getting. The props you're getting here is a Javascript object
and the spread operator pulls out all the properties that are inside of this props object and distributes
them as new key-value pairs on this wrapped component.
So if props here is a Javascript object with a name of Maximilian and an age of 28, then this syntax here
will effectively set name equal to Maximilian and age equal to 28, like this.
This is in the end what will happen here automatically behind the scenes for you. And therefore now
with this setup here,
if we save that, on the reloaded page, you'll see our data is back and it works just as it did before,
thanks to props being used and props being passed to the wrapped component here.