We learned a lot about higher order components,
let's go back to our regular components
so to say and there we have components like our app.js component here, our app component that do use
state.
This one is a class-based component
and what I want to show you now only matters for class-based components that use the state property
and that therefore use set state to update their state.
Now the good news is we're using set state correctly here,
bad news is you can use it incorrectly but I will show you how and how to avoid it.
So how could you use it in an invalid way?
Let's say that whenever our name changes and we execute the name changed handler, we want to count that,
so we essentially count every keystroke made or every change made.
So in our name changed handler here, we would not just want to update persons but also some counter
we keep track of. Now therefore we can of course add a counter to our state object, here
change counter and that starts at 0 and in named changed handler, we now call set state
and we set change counter equal
and now of course this always depends on the old state,
right?
Because we want to increment it by one,
so we need the old change counter plus one
and therefore of course we can say this state change counter plus one
and now we have a setup where we should increment the change counter. If I save this, let me bring up the
React developer tools so that we can actually inspect our current state of the app component.
So there we see the change counter
and if I toggle my persons and I start typing here, Maxmillian, you see this go up and you see that
go down.
So it seems to work, right
and yet it is the wrong way of updating this. Behind the scenes, set state does not immediately trigger
an update of the state of this component in a re-render cycle,
instead it's basically scheduled by React and React will then perform the state update and the re-render
cycle when it has the available resources to do that,
so when it basically decides that now is a good point of time to do that. Typically, that will of course
be instantly especially in simple applications like this one
but it's not guaranteed
and I want you to memorize this because that is really important.
You call set state synchronously here but it's not guaranteed to execute and finish immediately and
therefore, this state when used for a state update is not guaranteed to be the latest state or the previous
state on which you depend,
it could be an older state.
Let's say you're also calling set state somewhere else in your application which happens almost simultaneously
to this set state update and for some reason, this does not execute immediately and the other set state update
finishes earlier,
something like this. Then the state you depending on here might be an unexpected state, it might not be
the previous state you would expect it to be and therefore there is a better way of updating state when
you are depending on the old state. Set state does not only take a Javascript object, it also works when
you pass in a function, so you can use either syntax.
Now when you're doing state updates that don't depend on the old state, there is nothing wrong with just
passing the object,
so without the change counter, this is perfect. With the change counter however, you should use that optional
syntax where you actually receive two arguments and I'm using an anonymous arrow function here, where
the first argument is your old state and I'll name it prev state for previous state
and the second argument are your current props in case you need those. Then you have your function body
and in that function body, you should return this new state object, like this.
Now of course there, you are now not referring to this state but you can refer to previous state change
counter and here, React guarantees you that this will be the actual previous state as you would expect it
for this set state update.
So now if I save that, we'll see the exact same result as before.
So if I go in here and inspect my app and the change counter, as I start typing, it goes up and it goes
down or it stays up when I increase that I mean but it changes and that is the expected behavior
but this is the better way and the recommended way of updating the state when you're depending on old
state and therefore, you'll see me use that throughout the course whenever we do depend on old state. Super
important to keep that in mind,
it's an important pattern, not an optional solution but really the best practice for state updates that
depend on the old state.