By now, we had a super deep dive into many amazing features about React components and by the way, no
worries if that is getting a lot to remember,
you'll see a lot of that throughout this course, in the course project and in other modules.
So this is really just there to get it out of the way, to introduce you to a concept,
you'll see it applied then throughout this course and therefore, this will become clearer and clearer
as we use the different things you learned about.
We're not done yet though. In person component, we have that input where we can change the name of a person,
right? Now the approach or the way of changing this is absolutely fine here,
however if you want to get access to an HTML element like this input
but actually what I'm about to show you works with any HTML element, with any JSX element I
should say here,
then you are not limited to setting up two-way binding because that of course is nice for getting the
value you entered
but let's say you want to focus that input,
let's say when we render all our persons here, the last person should automatically receive focus.
Well then this is kind of hard to do here right,
how do we focus this? In regular Javascript,
you could of course write something like in componentDidMount, so right after this rendered
let's say, you could use document.querySelector, select your input and on that input, you could then
call the focus method.
Now if we try that actually and componentDidMount works here of course because it's a class-based component,
if I try that, then I do indeed focus but I focus the first one simply because document.querySelector
selects the first input it finds here and additionally, this is not really that great because it doesn't
refer to the input rendered by this component, otherwise it would render the last input because that
was the last component rendered,
so this code here actually executed the last time in that last person component and it didn't focus the
input of that person component but still, the first input it found on the entire page because document.querySelector
is not something that is related to React,
it is a general web or browser feature, a general DOM selector and it always works on the entire DOM,
it doesn't care whether we use React or not and therefore, this is not the optimal way of selecting this.
Sure we could set up an ID here to select it by ID but React actually has an easier way for us to
select an element, a concept called refs which stands for references. On any element and that does really
mean not just on inputs but on any element including your own components,
you can add a special ref keyword. Now ref, just like key, is a special property you can pass into any
component, it is detected and understood by React.
Now ref can be used in a couple of different ways and here is way number one which is supported in older
versions of React too. You pass a function here and this can be an anonymous arrow function as I'm doing
it here and the argument you're getting is a reference to the element you place this on,
so here we could name this inputEl but you can name it whatever you want. In that function body, you then
can use that,
therefore here of course, we could call focus actually but that's not what I want to do here,
instead let's say we want to use that in some other place of the application and therefore what you
can also do is, you can add a new property to your class, so not to your state but really just to the class
by using this, then any name of your choice like input element
but this can really be name, whatever you want
and this holds the inputEl
we're getting as an argument. So we're getting access to the input element here and then we're storing
this in a global property,
so from that point on we can use it anywhere in our application. And since componentDidMount executes
after render, input element will have been set by then,
so in here we can call input element focus, excuse me,
this input element focus of course because input element is a property of this class and therefore this approach
only works in class-based components, not in functional components. If we saved that, it reloads and
if I toggle my persons,
now the last persons input is selected, thanks to this reference.
Now this is one approach of using references but as I mentioned, it's not the only one. Since
React 16.3,
we also have another way of setting up a reference and that includes the constructor or requires us
to use the constructor
and in there, you can now set up your input element, so the same property I'm using down there, input element
by calling React create ref. So create ref is a method offered on the React object we're importing
and I'm storing it here in the input element.
Now that means of course this is not necessarily my input,
this is any reference object React gives me, whatever that is behind the scenes.
You can now use this reference here and therefore I'll name it inputEl, element ref to make it really
clear that this is just a reference, you can now use this here instead of passing a function to ref. So
this function approach is OK and therefore I'll comment it out to keep it here but you can now set ref
equal to this input element ref,
so to this property you're initializing here in the constructor. This holds an access to this ref object
React gives me and then I'm assigning this to my ref property and behind the scenes, React will make
the connection and input element ref will then actually allow me access to the element on which this
ref assignment was placed.
So now in componentDidMount, I can use this input element ref, so this ref property and there, I actually
have a current property which you have to access first
and this gives you access to your current reference.
So here, I'll access current and then focus because the current element stored in this reference here
is this element here,
so the input element and that does have a focus method.
So with that, we would always be able to do that.
Now one thing, if you add a constructor, you have to call super here and of course you should forward
the props you're getting here to make sure everything works correctly,
always when you add a constructor, add super first.
So now with that, we got everything set up and now this app reloads and you can see that still the last
person is selected,
thanks to our reference. So you can use either approach, either with React create ref which is the more
modern approach or by using that function form down there to get direct access to the element,
this is the older approach and therefore it also works in older versions of React and it's up to you
to use which version you want depending on which version, the version of React you're using, is allowing
you to use.