Now this how you can use refs in class-based components.
What about functional components, how do you use references there,
is it possible there?
Well this function-based approach here is not usable in functional components but the other approach
kind of is, with the help of React hooks.
So let's go into our cockpit.js file where we have a functional component and let's say in here, I
automatically want to click this button here whenever this entire page loads.
This is of course just a dummy example, you can implement any logic that fits your use cases.
So first of all, we need to set up a reference and since this is a functional component, we have no
constructor, we just have our function body.
So maybe up here, doesn't really matter but should definitely be before you return your JSX code of course,
you set up your reference. So I'll create a constant here and I'll name this toggle button ref
and now here in a class-based component, we would have used React create ref. In a functional component,
this will not work,
this is not supported but instead here we have a hook we can use, the use ref hook.
So you import use ref from React and then you use ref here, like this.
Now you could pass an initial value here because you can actually use references not just to get access
to DOM elements but you can even store other values in there but that is more advanced and not something
we'll dive into right now,
the more common use case here for references is that you do get access to your DOM elements.
So now we have our reference created with the help of the use ref hook,
now we can connect that in our DOM.
Now therefore let's pass null as an initial value here and then let's go down to our DOM or to our
JSX code to be precise,
not the real DOM
and here I want to pass a reference to this button or I want to set a reference to this button.
So here again, we use the ref key word, that can be used here as well
and I now refer to my button,
excuse me, my toggle button ref and toggle button ref is this constant which uses use ref.
Now with that set up,
we could try clicking that button. So let's use toggle button ref current click and let save this and
see if it works and it does and I get an error,
cannot read property click of null.
What's going wrong here,
do you have an idea?
It's kind of tricky but it's important, if you understand this, you understand how hooks work.
Well I'm getting this because I'm calling click right after I initialize my reference. React
didn't have a chance of executing the code down there where I actually do assign this reference to the
button and therefore at the point of time I'm calling click here, the button is of course undefined.
Now how could we change that? We can change this with useEffect because what did you learn about
useEffect?
It basically runs after every render cycle. So the function you pass to useEffect does not run immediately,
it runs after this JSX code here has been rendered for the first time and therefore useEffect
here is a great place to actually call click. So therefore here in this useEffect where I pass an empty
array as a second argument and which therefore only executes when the component renders the first time
and then cleans up when it's unmounted,
here I'll not use this set timeout thing anymore but instead here, I can now use toggle button ref current
click, like that.
And now if I reload this,
this works without error and you see indeed it does click the button otherwise we wouldn't instantly
see all the persons.
So that is how you can set references with the use ref hook, here when using React hooks in functional
components
and that also hopefully served as an example of how useEffect works and how it actually executes this
function
only after this JSX code was passed and rendered for the first time, so that React did have a chance
of connecting your reference here.