To conclude this module, we'll now dive into another exciting feature React offers you that can help you
avoid overly long chains of passing props around.
Now what do I mean by that?
Let me give you an example.
We have our person component here and let's say now we also manage some authentication status in this
application and I want to output whether we're authenticated down here in my person component,
I want to manage the authentication in the cockpit though.
So in the cockpit component, I'll add another extra button and add a caption of login, of course
that is totally up to you
and register an onClick listener and I don't want to manage my authentication status in here,
I just want to trigger a change to it with logging in here.
So I expect to get with a prop, a let's say login prop and of course you can choose any name you want.
Now we do use our cockpit component in the app.js file and in there, we now need to pass a login prop
because we're expecting this in a cockpit component,
we just added it here.
Now in the app.js file, we now need to add a method that does something when that login is triggered,
so when this button is clicked in a cockpit. For this, I'll add a new method here, authenticate or login
handler and all I want to do is I want to set some authentication state here to true.
So let's go to the state and in there, let's add authenticated and set this to false,
so by default the user is not authenticated let's say
and of course we're not adding real authentication here, we'll do this later in the app but not right
now
and in the login handler, I can then call this set state and set authenticated to true, like that.
The login handler is what I now pass to the cockpit component here on login,
so this login handler.
So all good,
now we're managing the authentication status in the app component but we want to use that in a person
component.
Now we only have access to the persons,
so multiple persons component in our app.js file.
So there we can pass our information let's say on an isAuthenticated prop and that prop name here is
of course totally up to you
and what I passed down is this state authenticated. In the persons component,
I'm not interested in that, I want to forward it to the person component.
So there, I can forward isAuth just to mix up the names,
this name is of course also up to you and I forward props isAuthenticated, so that prop we're passing
in from app.js here, isAuthenticated we're passing to persons, inside of persons, I'm forwarding
this to isAuth and this is a class-based component,
so it's this props of course. So now in person, we get isAuth as a property and in here, I can now ultimately
conditionally output a paragraph and check if this props isAuth, if this is true and then I want to output
a paragraph where I say authenticated and otherwise, I'll say please login.
Let's save that and see it in action.
This reloads, here is our login button and if I click that login button now, we see authenticated in
all these components.
So passing the data around works just as it should
and yet I am not really happy with my set up here because we're passing down props across multiple levels
and for example, the persons component really only forwards the authentication status. It receives is
authenticated as a prop but it doesn't really care
and this is not so great because it simply leads to extra redundancy and it makes our components a bit
less reusable because wherever we're using the persons component, we have to make sure we pass in is
authenticated so that we can forward it and there, we have a feature called context which helps us solve
the issue. Context was introduced by React and it helps us handle cases like this, where you need certain
data, certain state in multiple components and you don't want to pass that state across multiple layers
of components just to get it from component A at the top to component D at the very bottom when the
components B, C in between don't really care about it
and that's exactly the use case here.
We want to skip the persons component and with the React context feature, we can do that.
How does it work then?