I will add a new folder and name it context and you can name it whatever you want,
that of course does not matter and in there, I'll an auth-context.js file. In here,
I'll create a so-called context object and React gives us access to that,
so we need to import React from React and then I'll create my authContext here by calling React create
context and I'll export this authContext as a default for this file.
Now React create context actually allows us to initialize our context with a default value because what
the context in the end is is a globally available Javascript object
you could say, though globally available is not entirely correct,
you decide where it is available. But it is a Javascript object that can be passed between React components
without using props, behind the scenes so to say. So you can initialize as with any value you want,
for example here I'll set authenticated to false and I'll also add a login method here.
However this method will not do anything, it's an empty anonymous function and I'm adding this here because
if I initialize my default value with everything I want to be able to access on this context from different
components in my application, then I actually get better auto-completion from the IDE and that's the
only reason and I don't really care too much about that default value here otherwise because now that
authContext will be used in app.js and I will show you how to use it there and why doesn't matter what
you set as a default value. So in there,
let's import AuthContext with a capital A at the beginning from the context folder and there of course
the auth-context file. Now authContext can be used as a component and it should wrap and that's important,
it should wrap all the parts of your application that need access to this context.
In my case, that will be the cockpit component and the persons component which I'll output down there.
So this part here needs to be wrapped by my context,
this button doesn't really care and if I had other components being rendered in here and they don't
need authentication information, then they also don't need to be wrapped.
So down here, I will use my authContext which I imported now as a JSX element but not like this but
instead here, you can access with a .provider.
So this actually gives you a provider JSX component
on this authContext object and you wrap everything where you want to be able to access this context
later on.
So now inside of the cockpit and of persons, we'll be able to interact with our context and also in the
app.js file because here I'm setting up this provider component. Now the provider,
this component takes a value prop and this is why the default values here don't really matter,
the default value will apply when you don't set any other value. However in many use cases like this
one, you actually want to have a dynamic value,
the authentication status can change afterall and therefore, I'll manage the status here in app.js and
I pass my current state of the authentication status here to value. So value will be a Javascript object,
hence the double curly braces, outer curly braces are there to enter dynamic content, inner curly braces
construct Javascript object and there I'll have the exact same structure as here in the default context
object, so I'll have authenticated and login as keys and again, I did set it up here in my authContext
initialization because this now gives me better auto-completion in my IDE.
So in app.js, in this object here, we now have this authenticated key here and this should refer to this
state authenticated, so we'll still manage the authentication status in my state of this component because
one thing does not change when you use context,
React will re-render when state or props change. So only changing something in a context object would
not cause a re-render cycle and therefore this is not enough.
Hence I still manage my authentication status in the state of this component but I then also store
the current state in that authenticated prop of the object I am passing as a value to the authContext
and since this effectively is a prop of the authContext provider,
this will update whenever this state updates.
Now we also have the login key and that should point at my login handler,
so this just stores a reference to this login handler function.
Now this is in my context object that can now be accessed from cockpit and persons because they are
inside of the provider wrapper. So let's now access this inside of persons, how can we get access to our
authContext here?
First of all, we have to import it again. So I'll import AuthContext with a capital A from
and then you go up to the context folder and then authContext.
And now here we don't want to provide the context but we want to consume it and you do this by going
to the place where you return your JSX code, where you want to use that context and then you simply
use authContext.consumer as a JSX component
and this now wraps your other JSX code, since this is some Javascript expression, we need to wrap this
here with curly braces.
So now here, we have authContext.consumer but this is not yet the entirely correct syntax, authContext.consumer
does not take JSX code as a child, so as content between the opening and closing tag but
instead this takes a function as a child between the opening and closing tag.
So here, I actually will pass in a function which will eventually return my JSX code and this function
which will be executed for us by the authContext.consumer or by the React context API, this function will
get our context object,
so this is how we get access to that context object here in the place where we consume it. We provide
a function that accepts context as an argument, we'll get that argument by the authContext here, React
executes this function for us and then in this JSX code which we return here and which will be rendered
in the end, we have access to that context object and therefore now, we could forward this to isAuth. But
of course, that was not the idea here, right?
We wanted to use the authContext in person not in persons, we wanted to skip that extra cycle where
we have to forward something which we don't need in this component.
So let's actually not consume authContext in here,
let's remove that instead and let's also remove the isAuth prop we're forwarding and let's remove
the authContext import. We wanted to use authContext in the person component,
so here is the place where we should import it.
So import authContext from and now go all the way up to the context folder and import authContext
and now here I want to set up my consumer in the place where I want to access that context data
and for me, that is this single line here
and if you needed it in other places, you would wrap everything with that consumer where you need it.
So here I'll use my consumer
and as you learned, in there you get a function which gets context as an argument and then you have to
return the JSX code you eventually want to return,
so here I will grab this check here where I render a paragraph
and now, I could use my context here,
so I now use context authenticated.
With that, we're consuming our context in the person component to output the right data but we're not using
it for making this login button work.
So let's go back to the cockpit component now where we have that login button and let's consume context
here as well.
So first of all, let's import authContext from context, authContext and then let's consume it
here to wrap our login button.
So here I will use authContext.consumer, wrap this entire button
but of course as you learned, we don't just wrap the JSX code,
instead we wrap a function where we get the context argument and then this function returns the JSX code
and then again here, we can not access or we could access props login but we don't want to,
instead now we access context.login because remember, that login property holds a reference to
the login function, that is what we're setting up here.
And now we don't need to pass this login handler on the login peop to cockpit anymore,
instead we're now using context. And now once everything saves, we can press login and it updates as
before
but now we're using the context API. And this is especially useful if you have very long chains of data
you're passing around and if you don't want to pass data from component to component to component, if you
don't need it in these in-between components, then context is a great way of bypassing components and
directly passing data from A to D.