We learned about the context API and this way of using it is perfectly fine but there is a more elegant
way for using it in class-based components
and of course, there also is an alternative way for using it in functional components,
so let's have a look at these two alternative ways
now. Now let's start in the person component which is a class-based component. In class-based components and
only there, you can use an alternative pattern to using that authContext consumer that gets this function
because not only is this code a bit verbose and can be tricky to wrap your head around when you see it
the first time,
it also only gives you access to the context in your JSX code here, where you render authContext consumer.
Now what if you wanted to have access to it in componentDidMount because here you also need the authentication
status because you are maybe sending an HTTP request
that needs the user ID?
Well then you would have no chance to access the context in componentDidMount when injecting or when
using the context like this.
Thankfully, React 16.6
added another way of using context. You can add a special static property named contextType.
Now this has to be named contextType, written exactly like this and it has to be a static property. Static
property means that
it can be accessed from outside without the need to instantiate an object based on this class first
and React will access contextType for you, so to say. Now we set a value here and that value should be
your authContext, just like this,
not as JSX code,
nothing else,
just the authContext object.
Now this allows React to automatically connect this component here,
this class-based component to your context behind the scenes and it gives you a new property in this
component, the this context property. We can now console log
this context here and again, this context, it has to be written like this because this is given to you
by React automatically
and there, we can access login for example or authenticated which was our context
property holding true or false.
This allows us to get access to our context even in places like componentDidMount where we previously
couldn't.
And you can of course also use this context in your render function,
so instead of using authContext consumer here, you can get rid of that like this and like this and instead
wrap this here with curly braces because we have some Javascript code here, not just JSX and now
here it's this context, referring to this context property React gives you.
And if you now save that, you see in your console log, false here three times because we have three persons
and that is your authentication context being logged and you see please login is shown because we're
not authenticated. And if I press login,
this changes because this works entirely as before
but now with this more convenient static context type. Now this can be used in class-based components
and I recommend using it there because it's shorter, it's easier in my opinion and it gives you access
to contexts in places where you previously had no access. In functional components,
this is not available.
So there, we right now only can use authContext consumer because you can't set up a static property here.
Thankfully, React has you covered with hooks.
You can import the use context hook and this now allows you to get access to your context anywhere in
your functional component function body, like here. There I could have my authContext and you can name
this whatever you want and you simply use context like this and as an argument, you of course pass your
authContext object
and here again, React will make the connection for you behind the scenes.
So now authContext will be a constant that holds information about your authContext data.
So here we can console log authContext authenticated for example and we can of course also use that
in our JSX code down there.
So let's get rid of authContext consumer and of that function syntax and just output the JSX code for
the button and here instead of context, we now use authContext,
so this constant I just created. And now with that saved, if I press login,
it still works
as before now using the used context hook. So use context is to functional components
what static context type is to class-based components you could say. It gives you access to the context
and the context, the context API is all about managing data across components without the need to pass
data around with props. We'll also learn a different concept that helps us with this, Redux later in the
course and we'll use Redux later in the course
but knowing the context API is important because you can build exciting things with that and it will
also make it easier to understand that Redux thing later
once we dive into that.