Now that was a lot to digest,
this was a real deep dive module. You learned a lot about React components,
a lot of cool features, some niche features and a lot of features you will encounter throughout this course.
Take this module as a reference module,
feel free to come back to this module whenever you see something in the course where you're not sure
about how it works
or whenever you're working on your own project and you need to use context or you need to use the component
lifecycle. Come back to this module and use this module like a little API reference, showing you
a lot of advanced or special features of React components that you might need in one use case or the
other.
And as I mentioned, you will see a lot of these features being used throughout this course which will
certainly help with understanding and applying them but don't feel bad if you have to go back through
a video and go through a certain concept.
Again, my goal and intention with this module was and is to give you a broad overview of the many things
you can do with React components, how you can optimize them and how React gives you a lot of different
features for different problems
you might be facing.