So now that we optimize our little demo application here,
let me dive into that stateless versus stateful or presentational versus container component
thing again because that is really important to understand when working with React because you'll hear
it a lot.
Now we're referring to stateful components when we're managing state in them, like we're doing in
the app.js. We got state here and we're calling set state to change that state.
Now a functional component that manages its own state with the useState would of course also be a
stateful component, so stateful does not automatically mean class-based component,
though historically this has been the case because React hooks like useState are a really new feature
and therefore, you will still find plenty of applications where state is only managed in class-based
components.
Still since React 16.8, stateful is not automatically a class-based component. It is a component
that manages state, he that with state in a class or with the useState hook. Presentational, also called
dumb or stateless components historically have always been functional components because prior to React
16.8, these functional components could not manage state. Since React 16.8, functional
components can also manage state with the useState hook but still, you want to have many presentational
components in your app and now what is a presentational component? It is a functional component that
does not manage state. Even though you could with useState, it is still a good practice to restrict yourself
to a couple of components that are involved in the state management and of course, a couple depends on
how big your app is, in big apps that can easily be hundreds of components but the majority of your components
should be presentational, stateless components, so functional components that don't manage state. Now
the question of course is why and the answer is by splitting your app into container components which
is another term for these components that manage the state in your app and the dumb presentational components,
by making that split, you keep your app manageable because you have a predictable flow of data, you know
where your state changes, that will be in a couple of components and the other components are only there
to render a nice user interface and they only define on external inputs, on props and that simply ensures
that these components are highly predictable, that you can throw them anywhere into your application
and they work if you pass the right inputs in and as your application grows, you therefore have an easier
time maintaining it.
So having a lot of dumb or presentational components is a good idea.
Now of course, you definitely should not restrict yourself to one component only that does state management
though. The more you work with React, the more you'll get a feeling for which component now should manage
some state so that its child components get the right inputs and which components would better be just
presentational components but again as a rule, certainly think before you start managing state in a
component, maybe you can do it in another component and keep that component you're working on a presentational
one. So that is how you should think about stateful and stateless or container and dumb or presentational
components.
We also of course have class-based and functional components and in the past, the difference was very easy.
Class-based components could manage state, functional components couldn't, since React 16, that changed.
So what's the difference now, when should you use which?