With class-based and functional components, it's important to understand which kind of component can
do what, what their history is and what their future is. So class-based components,
with that I simply mean components that extend that component object
we can import from the React package and functional components are simply these functions that take
props and return some
JSX code. Now these components do differ
when it comes to managing state and to something called lifecycle hooks which we haven't had a look
yet but which we'll dive into in this section. Class-based components can access state and they can change
it with set state and they also can use these lifecycle hooks as you will learn. Functional components,
there it's a bit tricky. In the past before React
hooks were introduced, they couldn't manage state but since React hooks were introduced, they can with
the useState hook.
So access to state is actually possible but lifecycle hooks are still not supported.
Functional components are way more powerful than they have been in the past though and the difference
between class-based components and functional components therefore is way less strong than it used to
be.
What's important to note though that not every React project you might be working on will use the latest
version of React and therefore, it's still important to be aware of the fact that historically, state
management could only be done in class-based components and therefore you had to transform your
components to class-based components if you wanted to access state. And actually in this course,
I will have that split where all components where I use state are class-based and only towards the end
or later down the course,
I will also show you how to convert the entire course project we'll build to a hooks-based approach simply
because majority of projects still use that class-based approach and I want you to learn both approaches.
Now regarding the way we access state and also props, it's important to know that in class-based components,
you need the this keyword because state and props are properties of the component class and we haven't
used this props yet, we'll do so in this video still but just keep that in mind, you need the this keyword
there.
In functional components, you get props as an argument and therefore you can just use it like this, like
a normal variable in your function.
So when should you use what? When you're using a version of React that doesn't support React hooks,
the answer is simple. When you're working with state or you need lifecycle hooks, use the class-based approach.
If you're in a project that uses React hooks, it's less simple.
You might want to use functional components only but as we'll doing this course, you can also still split
it to have a clear separation between components that are involved with state management and components
that aren't and as it's optimal to have as many presentational only components as possible,
this might make it easier for you to keep that separation between stateful and stateless components.
So use class by components if you need to manage state or access to lifecycle hooks and you don't want
or you can't use React hooks,
use functional components in all other cases.
So if you can use React hooks and you use the right versions of React and you want to use it, go functional
and do your state management in there and you will learn what replaces lifecycle hooks in this module
too.
If you are using an older version of React, then use functional components for all your presentational
components, so all the components that only get inputs, props and don't need to manage state. Now regarding
that the this state and the this props thing,
I haven't really shown you what I meant by that. Now
thus far we only access this state here in the app.js file, we access this state to pass our state to the
cockpit component for example.
Now the app.js file here simply doesn't receive any props or the app component doesn't receive any props
but we can change this. In our index.js file,
we can of course send a prop into our app component simply by setting it here,
for example our app title, our application title. That could be our person manager because we're clearly
managing some persons,
so I'm sending this string on the app title prop into my app component
and now if I want to use it in there, I need to use the this keyword. So in app.js, I could now use this
prop anywhere in here
but I actually want to forward it to the cockpit.
So there, I'll add a title prop and you could name this prop whatever you want
and if I now want to access the property of this app component, I do this on this props
and then there, it's app title,
that was the name of the prop I set in the index.js file and here I'm just passing that through to
the cockpit.
So in the cockpit if I go there, I will now have that new title property which I can use to output my
title down there,
so instead of Hi I'm a React app, I'll now output props.title and here it's just props.title
because this is not a class, therefore we don't need to use this to access the props.
It's important to keep that difference in mind as well.
With that, if we go back to our application, we see the person manager up there. The rest works as it did
before.