I also mentioned this component lifecycle in the last lecture,
what is the component lifecycle?
The first important takeaway is, it's only available in class-based components.
You will actually learn that functional components when using React hooks have an equivalent
you could say but generally, it's only available in class-based components, that lifecycle and I will
show you both of course, the lifecycle and the functional component equivalent
in this module. So let's start with the class-based lifecycle.
We've got these methods which we can add to any class-based component and React will execute them for
us and they will run at different points of time and we can do different things with them, to for example
fetch data from the web or to do some cleanup work before a component is removed from the DOM. But how
exactly can we use them and in which order do they execute? Let's start with the component lifecycle
during the component creation
because we actually have to differentiate between lifecycle hooks that run whenever something changes
in our component, some props for example and the lifecycle that runs when a component is rendered for
the first time because it's rendered as part of a list
or because we only conditionally show it.
So when a component is created, then first of all the constructor executes.
Now this is actually not a React lifecycle hook,
instead it's a default
ES6 class feature,
the important thing there is this constructor will receive the props of this component and you have
to call super props in the constructor. Only if you add it, so you don't have to add it just to make that
call,
it's done for you if you don't add it but if you add your own constructor where you will want to execute
your own logic, you need to call super props in there and I'll show you all of that in action right after
these slides here,
no worries.
Now what is the constructor
therefore? You can do it for basic initialization work, for example for setting an initial state.
What you shouldn't do here is cause side effects.
Now the word side effect is relatively abstract,
in the end it means things like sending a HTTP request or storing something in your local storage of the
browser or sending some analytics to Google analytics.
You don't really want to do things like that in the constructor because that can impact performance and
cause unnecessary re-render cycles which of course are pretty bad and you want to avoid. After the constructor,
getDerivedStateFromProps runs. That is a lifecycle hook that was added With React 16.3 and
in the end, the idea here is that whenever your props change for your class-based component, you can sink
your state to them and that will actually be very rare niche cases,
let me be very honest, you'll not use that lifecycle hook a lot but if you have some scenario where props
of your component can change and then you want to update some internal state of that component, then
this is the hook to use and I will show you how that hook works as well.
Now what you shouldn't do in there still is causing side effects,
don't send HTTP requests in that hook,
there are better places for that. Now after these two hooks, the render method executes.
We already know that, that is the method that returns JSX and that is really its job.
You should use it only to prepare the data as you need it to lay out your JSX code and to render the
HTML code so to say. What you still shouldn't do in there is send HTTP requests or set any timeouts,
so nothing which can block this rendering process. Now when render runs and you do render any other React
components in this class-based component,
then these child components will now be rendered.
So every child component you included in your rendered component here will then be rendered as well
and only once all child components were rendered and that their lifecycle looks finished, your lifecycle
hook here will finish for the creation when componentDidMount gets called. componentDidMount is
a very important lifecycle hook which you'll use a lot when you're working with class-based components
because here, you can cause side effects.
That is a typical hook you would use for making an HTTP request to get new data from the web.
What you shouldn't do in here is update the state,
so don't call set state in here unless it's in, let's say the then block of a promise after you sent
an HTTP request but don't call set state in here synchronously. So you can definitely set up some code
that executes in the future which then updates the state,
for example when the response from the server is back but don't do it right away when componentDidMount
runs that you immediately call set state because that will trigger a re-render cycle and that is
bad for performance.
Let's have a look at this in practice.