Just as we have a lifecycle for the component creation, we also have one for updating components.
So when props or state change which are the two triggers you have for a component to be re-evaluated
by React,
then we go through a different lifecycle.
This lifecycle then starts with getDerivedStateFromProps being called, a lifecycle method which
you'll not use too often, you would use it to initialize the state of a component that updates based
on props you're getting, so updated props you're getting most likely and that could be for example some
form control which gets external properties and then you internally want to handle user input but initialize
your state or update your state based on outside changes
and as you will see throughout this course, we'll not use that lifecycle hook because actually, you very
very rarely need that and often there is a more elegant way of updating your state or of managing your
components based on external properties.
Nonetheless this hook exists, it's there for you to sync your local state inside of the component to
your props you're getting, you should not cause side effects in here so don't send any HTTP requests
or anything like that.
Thereafter we reach shouldComponentUpdate and that is a very interesting hook indeed which I'll dive
deeper into in the next lectures.
This method and by the way, I use the term lifecycle methods and lifecycle hooks interchangeably,
so this lifecycle method or hook here is interesting because it allows you to cancel the updating process.
So here you can decide whether or not React should continue evaluating and re-rendering the component.
Now why would you do that? For performance optimization as you will learn over the next lectures.
This should be used carefully because obviously, you can break your components if you block an update
from happening incorrectly but it is very powerful since it allows you to also prevent unnecessary update
cycles.
Now after that, the render method is called and React then goes through the JSX code, evaluates that and
basically constructs its virtual DOM into which I'll also dive later in this module for you and sees
if it needs to update the real DOM.
Now there as always you prepare and structure your JSX code
therefore. Now React then goes ahead and updates all child components of this component, so it evaluates
all the child components you have in your JSX code of this main component we're looking at here for
which this lifecycle here runs
and of course every child component then also goes through that lifecycle if it receives new props or
state.
Now after that, we reach getSnapshotBeforeUpdate.
This is a lifecycle hook that takes the previous props and the previous state as input and that actually
returns a snapshot object which you can freely configure and this also is a niche lifecycle hook which
we'll not use too much,
you use it for last minute DOM operations but with that, I don't really mean changes to the DOM but things
like getting the current scrolling position of the user.
So imagine that your upcoming update of your component will re-render the DOM and will add new elements
on the DOM and you therefore  want to restore the scrolling position of the user wants the update is done.
Well then getSnapshotBeforeUpdate can give you that snapshot of the user state,
so of the scrolling position right before the update happens and then you can consume and use that
snapshot once the update is done to scroll the user back to where he was or anything like that.
And last but not least once we're done with the update, componentDidUpdate
is called. A lifecycle hook that signals that you are now done with the updating, that the
render method has been executed
and here you can now cause side effects,
so here you could now make an HTTP request, though you'll have to watch out to not enter an infinite loop
here
if you make an HTTP request and you get back a response and you then update your component and
then this cycle starts again and that is also something we'll have a look at later in this course
once we dive into HTTP requests because there, this is a typical problem you'll be facing. Now what you
shouldn't do here outside of the,
let's say then block of a promise of an HTTP request is updating the state with set state.
It's fine to do it as a result of some async task you're kicking off here but you should not call it
synchronously in componentDidUpdate because that will simply lead to an unnecessary re-render cycle.
So let's now have a look at all these lifecycle methods in practice and let's start with the scenario
that our props changed. To see these update lifecycle looks in practice,
I will convert persons and person component to class-based components so that we can throw some lifecycle
hooks into these as well,
now let's start with the person.js file. Converting a component to a class-based component is very
simple, you simply import component from React because we'll need to extend that and then instead of
returning a function or having a function that you store in a variable or constant here, you create a
new class which you typically name with a capital starting character like Person, that extends component
and then you have opening and closing curly braces but in there, you now need a render method which actually
returns your JSX code.
So in there, you can then move in this console log and there, you should now add this return statement
where you return the JSX code. And that is almost it but props doesn't exist anymore,
instead all these places where you have props now should become this.props because as you learned in
class-based components, props are accessed with the this keyword since they are properties of this class.
So let's add this in front of all these props and here we go,
that is the converted person component.
Last thing we need to change is the export, there
I am exporting person with a lowercase P because my constant was named such,
now the class has an uppercase P, so here I should update person like that
and this is now the converted person component. Now definitely feel free to now convert the persons
component on your own
and after the short pause which you can use to pause the video, we'll do it together. So were you successful?
Let's convert the persons component and just as before,
first of all I will import component from React
and then here, this is converted to a class named persons which extends component, opening and closing
curly braces, in there a render method and in that render method, we can throw in our return statement
where we return JSX code, like this.
Now again, props doesn't exist
so this becomes this.props here and then we export Persons with a capital P and that is it.
That's the adjusted persons component and of course the app works just as before, like this and you
see I also get a warning regarding componentWillMount by the way but we can ignore that
as I mentioned, this will be removed eventually but in older versions of React, you can still use it. Here,
the focus is on our conversion of the class-based component or of the functional components to class-based
components which work just fine. So let's now see these updating lifecycle hooks in action. I'll start
here in my persons.js component and I'll start with the static getDerivedStateFromProps lifecycle
hook again which gets props and state, should return a state and here I'll return the unchanged
state and I don't even have a state here, so this will just be an empty object and I want to console
log persons.js getDerivedStateFromProps, like this.
Thereafter, shouldComponentUpdate will run and shouldComponentUpdate gets the next props, so the upcoming
props which will have an effect right after this update which is about to take place and the upcoming
state as arguments and in here,
now you actually have to return true or false,
doing nothing is not an option. You have to return true if React should continue updating or false if
it shouldn't
and of course you don't typically hardcode then in here but instead you add some condition where you
compare the current props to your next props, to the upcoming props to find out if they changed and if
they changed, you want to permit this.
For now I will just return true here though and I'll dive a bit deeper into this in a dedicated lecture
in this module.
So let me console log persons.js shouldComponentUpdate.
After shouldComponentUpdate, we have getSnapshotBeforeUpdate and there we get our previous props
and we get our previous state and I will console log
persons.js getSnapshotBeforeUpdate
here. Now after getSnapshotBeforeUpdate, render will execute and I already have a login here,
then the render cycle or the update cycle of all child components of this component will execute,
so of all the person components in this case and thereafter, we'll have componentDidUpdate and
componentDidUpdate will run once we're done with all the updating.
So here, I will console log persons.js componentDidUpdate, like this. Let's have a look at that and
to get rid of that error regarding componentWillMount, I'll comment this out, only older versions of React
will support this and what we see is now our default rendering cycle for creating the component. If I click
toggle persons, you see what happens is getDerivedStateFromProps runs again,
then render and then you see here I get a warning that in my persons, I have getDerivedStateFromProps
and in there, I am indeed returning a new state here
but since I have an uninitialized state, it's not recommended using that lifecycle hook basically
and therefore, you typically would want to get rid of that,
I will do that to get rid of that warning,
it's not an error but it again doesn't make sense to have it here if we don't do anything with that
state and we don't even have an initial state
but it did execute, that is something you could see. And then we had our rendering cycles here for the
different components.
Now what about componentDidUpdate though,
where's that?
Well it's nowhere to be seen because right now, we weren't in the update cycle of our persons component.
getDerivedStateFromProps
only ran because it's also part of the creation lifecycle. The update lifecycle of persons.js will
run as soon as I, for example, type something here because then, we'll actually trigger, if you have a look
at your input in person component, we'll trigger this onChange handler which triggers this props changed.
This props changed in person.js here is forwarded to the changed prop of the persons component which
is forwarded to our app.js file and in there if we have a look, changed calls the name changed handler
and this updates our persons which we pass back in as a property to the persons component and
therefore in this component,
now the updating lifecycle will begin because we forwarded that event from a child to the parent component
to the app component,
there we updated its state and then we got new data as a prop into this persons component and therefore
this persons component lifecycle triggers as soon as we type.
So let's type something and
let me clear the console before I do that and you see now getDerivedStateFromProps runs,
then render, then shouldComponentUpdate, then rendering also for the three persons,
then getSnapshotBeforeUpdate where I get a warning that I need to return a snapshot value or null
and we should actually do that, so let's simply return null here, let it reload, clear that and type
one character again,
now we have no warning and then we have componentDidUpdate. Now in case you're wondering about that snapshot,
that snapshot is a data package
so to say which you then receive in componentDidUpdate, so that you can save some state right before
the update, like the scroll position I mentioned and then you can use it to update the DOM again or update
the scrolling of the user let's say in componentDidUpdate once the DOM has been re-rendered and to demonstrate
this here, I'll just return an object with a message of snapshot.
Of course in reality you would probably again return something like some coordinates for the scrolling
and then in componentDidUpdate, you actually get the previous props, the previous state,
so before the update in case you need that for anything and the last argument is that snapshot
and if I now console log that snapshot here, you should see that we log a message or an object with
that message of snapshot.
So let's toggle the persons, type one character and indeed here, we have that output from componentDidMount
.
So that is how you can use that snapshot to save some data before the update and then use it after the
update
and that is the general component updating flow.
Now I mentioned earlier that there are some lifecycle hooks which we had in the past which aren't really
supported anymore and which you should not use if possible,
that was componentWillMount, now for updating, we have two other hooks. There first of all, we have component
will receive props and there, you will actually get the props you are getting for this update.
So here we can console log persons.js componentWillReceiveProps and also the props
and if we do that, then we try updating, then you actually see I get that same warning we had before with
componentWillReceiveProps,
so this setup will not even let me use that. In older apps, that would have worked and yes it is removed
because it was kind of a niche thing. You could have used that for updating some internal state but it
was easy to use this incorrectly and therefore you shouldn't use it anymore and the other hook which
will also be removed or which is already not supported by some workflows is componentWillUpdate.
In the past, you had componentWillUpdate here and that ran right before componentDidUpdate
and again, it was kind of hard to justify using this hook, it was often used incorrectly and therefore
this is now also removed but if you are seeing this in older projects, it was a hook that existed historically,
that technically still could be used but that shouldn't be used anymore because you never really needed
it. If you needed it, you were probably using React incorrectly and that's why it's not available anymore.