That was the updating lifecycle for prop changes.
Most important takeaway, the hook you'll use by far most often will be componentDidUpdate which is
after the update finished when you for example need to fetch new data from a server.
Let's now also have a look at the lifecycle hook for internal changes when the state changes and
we can do that with the help of app.js. In there, we do change the state
after all when people enter something into one of our person inputs and therefore in there,
let's also add after componentDidMount, componentDidUpdate and you could also add the get snapshot
before update hook in here if you wanted to. I'll leave it to be and just add componentDidUpdate and I'll
add one other hook before componentDidUpdate and that will be shouldComponentUpdate where I get
my next props and my next state and therefore here, I will also console log app.js
shouldComponentUpdate.
Let's see if these hooks are triggered as well.
So if I reload here, toggle persons, then I actually fail,
do you know why?
Well, it basically actually gives us the reason here. shouldComponentUpdate as I mentioned earlier has
to return something
and if you're returning undefined
this is basically treated as false and therefore blocks the update.
So if I return false here for example to make this even clearer, I'll not get the warning anymore but
toggling will not work because I'm preventing the update, here
the update would be necessary though because the update would render all these person items but if I'm
preventing it because I know better, well then this is not going to happen.
Of course, we'll learn the smart way of using shouldComponentUpdate in this module too.
So for now, I'll just set this to true to always allow the update which by the way is also the default
if you don't include this hook, then it also always lets React go ahead.
So now we see that again
and now if I type one character, we see we get the update from app.js, getDerivedStateFromProps then
we get shouldComponentUpdate here, render, then we we're in the persons.js updating hook and then
in the end, we're at componentDidUpdate for app.js. So we spend a lot of time on all these lifecycle
hooks and knowing them is important. When you're working with class-based components,
it's important that you know how they actually are created and where you can execute your custom code
during that lifecycle process.
Important, componentDidMount, componentDidUpdate and also for performance improvements, shouldComponentUpdate
are the most important hooks because in componentDidMount and componentDidUpdate, you will
typically do things like fetching new data from a server, shouldComponentUpdate,
well we'll dive into that again in this module, can be used for performance improvements.
But what about functional components?
I mentioned that the lifecycle is only available for class-based components and prior to the introduction
of React hooks, functional components had nothing that would compare to that which was fine because we
only use them for presentational purposes.
But now with React hooks, you can actually build your entire React app with functional components only
because you can manage the state in there. So you should also have a tool for running some code whenever
the component updates or when it is created and therefore what is the equivalent to these lifecycle
hooks for functional components?