Welcome to discourse about react.
It's great to have you on board.
My name is Maximilian Schwartz Miller and I'm a freelance web developer.
Andrew react developer I worked with react a lot and I can tell you it's an amazing library for creating
highly reactive and super fast javascript driven Web applications.
The javascript driven part is especially important because since react is a javascript library it's
of course about writing your web apps in JavaScript and that in turn is amazing because since javascript
runs in the browser it allows you to create super fast Web apps that feel like mobile apps.
Users don't have to wait for petrol loads now react is probably the most popular javascript library.
You can learn these days and for a good reason you will learn all of its core features for all this
course.
And way more than that you will learn what react is about how it works and why you might want to use
it.
You will learn how to build components which react how to use read Acts for better state management
how to use to react router and you'll not just learn as in simple projects or theory no.
We will build an entire react application throughout this course.
The burger Boulder which is an amazing application utilizing all the concepts you learn in this course
so that you have a really solid understanding of all the concepts taught throughout this course by the
end of the course.
You'll therefore have way more than just a solid understanding of react and you'll be able to dive deeper
into more challenging projects and apply for react developer chops or become a react developer as a
freelancer whatever your goal is.