Let's start with prop types.
Right now we're doing prop type validation in the burger ingredient component.
There we make sure that the type is set,
so it's required and that it is a string.
I'm not doing any validation in any other component
and the reason for this is that here I'm not working on a project which is going to get used by other
people,
I'm not working on the third-party library,
I am not even working in a developer team,
so a lot of the reasons why properties might be used incorrectly aren't relevant here.
Additionally, we'll get logical errors in our application
if we forget or assign a wrong key property anyways and that is why I don't use prop type validation
that much in this application.
Feel free as a practice to add prop types validation to more components. You can convert them to class
based components for that or keep them as functional components, doesn't really matter,
I typically convert it in class-based components also to highlight the difference and to make it really
clear that I'm adding prop type validation
but you don't need to do that and I will not add them to all my components but you can definitely do
this as a practice.