So these were my two cents about prop types,
what about pure components and shouldComponentUpdate? We're not using that in the application,
now let's analyze the application.
Do we have any state or prop changes which trigger a re-rendering even though this might not be required?
If we have a look at the running application, most clicks and things we do really change the UI
and therefore should trigger updates, should trigger a re-rendering of these components.
So we shouldn't really lose performance there and using a lot of pure components for unnecessary
shouldComponentUpdate checks might even hit the performance more than doing an occasional unnecessary re-rendering.
Crucial points we should check
are of course our burger builder container, there we change the state but whenever we do change the state,
it really affects our application and we do need to re-render stuff.
I can identify one element here though where we might be able to save some performance by not re-rendering
it unnecessarily
and that is the modal component. It wraps the order summary and that of course means that whenever ingredients
or the price changes, since these are props of order summary, order summary will be re-rendered.
However if the modal is not visible, we don't need to do that.
So actually only if the modal is shown, re-rendering of that wrapped element here makes sense.
So that is something we might want to check and control,
so let's first of all find out when order summary is re-rendered by simply adding a lifecycle hook
to it.
So I'll go to order summary and currently this is of course a functional component,
let's turn it into a class component so that we can add lifecycle hooks, so that we can see when this
is updated.
So let's extend the component object which we of course now need to import from React and in there as
you learned it,
we need to have a render method where we need to return our JSX code,
so basically this code here. Now we also have some adjustments here, the ingredient summary we calculate,
so let's do that prior to returning the JSX code but inside the render method and now we can get rid
of that stuff down there and we need to adjust the exported name and props now always are this props
as you learned, that's the case in class-based components.
So with that,
what else is missing? Here we go
also props,
so that should be this props here too.
Now with that saved, it should work again, should be working fine,
let's now implement method to see when this actually updates, I'll add componentWillUpdate here.
Now if that fails for you because your React version maybe doesn't support it anymore, well you can also
simply use componentDidUpdate, in the end
I just want to highlight here that we're in the updating process,
it doesn't have to be componentWillUpdate and we'll not use this hook here for anything important.
So definitely no need to implement componentWillUpdate here,
componentDidUpdate will do and I simply want to console log orderSummary will update.
Now let's see when this updates. If we reload the application and I add an ingredient, you'll see order
summary will update
even though we're not showing it, so it doesn't necessarily make a lot of sense to re-render that.
Now let's see if that changes, if we make sure that modal doesn't update unnecessarily and for that,
let's head over to the modal.js file and let's also turn modal into a class so that we can implement
shouldComponentUpdate.
Alternatively of course, you could keep this as a functional component and wrap the exported component,
so the modal constant you're exporting with React.memo.
This would be an alternative to using shouldComponentUpdate, both works and both will effectively have
the same impact and effect here.
So modal will therefore also extend component, let's import component from React then and export the
renamed modal and of course also now, make sure to implement the class body with a render method where
we now return our JSX code, like this
here and get rid of that stuff down there which we don't need anymore
and as always make sure that props become this props.
So now the modal is working again and let's now see if we can control the updating of order summary
which is wrapped by the modal by changing the way the modal itself updates.
So let's simply add shouldComponentUpdate to the modal and we'll get the next props and next state
here as arguments,
so now I want to check or now I might want to make sure that this only updates if show changes because
that's the only thing which matters for me here.
So if next props show, if that is unequal to this props show, so to the previous state, then I want to return
true or we can of course simply shorten this and simply return the result of this check,
so that is what I want to do here. Let's now also implement componentWillUpdate here to confirm if
this works, so I will simply console log modal will update and save this component now.
Now let's see, if I now reload the page and I start adding elements, we see order summary is not calling
will update anymore, if I click order now,
now modal will update is called and order summary will update is called.
So here, we definitely improved our application because we make sure that we don't unnecessarily update
order summary, that we don't unnecessarily re-render that
and you also see that the wrapping element controls the updating of the wrapped element. So order summary
theoretically, the component, is included in the burger builder but it is not updated because the wrapping
element modal has a shouldComponentUpdate method where we control this.
Now our code here is pretty lean in the modal and what we don't do, we don't react to changes in the
clicked listener,
so if the modal closed property would change, we're not checking this,
so we only return true if show changed.
It's okay here in this application because we actually never reassign this click listener.
If we were to do that or if we were to also change state in the modal, we definitely should also check
for changes in other props, in other state properties or simply extend pure component. Here
I'm not using pure component because pure component would run more checks than I want to do,
pure component would also check for modal closed to be changed and I'm not interested in that,
so my method should be even more straightforward, even more focused. Now with that, we can of course also
turn our order summary back into a functional component to no longer output componentWillUpdate here
but I'll leave it in here for debugging purposes, for reference
but I will comment that this could be a functional component,
doesn't have to be a class
and of course componentWillUpdate is not required. shouldComponentUpdate is definitely not required
here because we don't need to check this,
this always needs to be updated
if the modal is shown and the modal is where we do check whether it needs to be updated or not.
So this is one improvement we can add to this application.