Now that the planning is done let's dive into the project and let's actually build this application
forward as I opened a brand new project created with create a react app.
Nothing has been changed here yet.
Now you can either create a new project on your own or you simply used to attach starting Project which
reflects this exact state you see here on my screen to start on the same page as I do now in this project.
I first of all want to enable see as modules so that I can make sure that they see us as class as we
create in a C as as file can be scoped to a specific component in our application so that they are not
applied globally when we would accidentally reuse the same CSF class.
For that I need to eject the project.
As you learned so let's do that first let's run NPM run eject in the newly created Project and this
will now ask us if we really want to eject.
So I will confirm this with Y for yes and now as we saw it before in the module where I showed you how
to implement C as as module you get access to the config in a conflict folder and there to do to web
pack configuration files.
Now let's dive into the first of the two and search for the part where you have to use CSR as test and
to see us as loader there.
As I showed you in the mentioned module you have to add modules true to the options off that loader
and add you local ident name option to basically define DC as as class name.
It will automatically generate and assign this should take your original name then two underscores then
the local name of the component and then a randomly generated hash with hash coal base 64 colon 5.
This will generate these unique see us as class names which are then assigned automatically once we
import them through that object from the CSA s file.
As I showed you in that module now copy these two lines with modules and local ident name and go to
the ABA webpage conflict fall to it this convict file for the production build and of course there we
also want to ensure that we can use C as US modules so enter it here in the options.
Make sure to close that string here.
Entered here in the options for DC as its loader so that both webpage conflict files have been adjusted
and saved.
And with that we got our project set up and we can get started.
Now let's do some cleanup work let's remove that logo dot SPG file which was created automatically I
don't be dead and in the aptly as fall we can get rid of the import of that fall therefore we can also
clean up the app J.S. content here removed a class name from the div and remove the app CSX import here
even and remove DMC as as as.
I don't need to styling here right now I will leave the global styling here though but in the next year
as file where I set up my global body style and which I still import normally in quotation marks by
referencing the file and not importing a class object so therefore it will get applied globally in that
CSR as file I want to set the font family to a number of font we could of course use that but I picked
a different one which I find a bit more beautiful.
Basically I want to use open sense and for that you can simply search for a Google funds and on the
Google funds page as it just mentioned it's does open the sense fall here.
Now once you selected this you can click on that the bottom to customize it and there.
I don't just want to pick the regular one let's all to pick up the bold one in case we need this.
In case you want to have some bold text for example for headings.
Now with that let's go to embed and there you find a link to the Google sedan from which you can import
this fund and those perfectly find is exactly the approach L and I use.
So now with that link let's go back to our project folder to the public folder into the index h t email
file and there I will added right above the title.
Now speaking of the title I'll also justice to my burger because well this should be the name of my
application here.
With that D set off the project is pretty much finished.
We can now start writing our ReACT application and implement that component tree we designed in the
last lectures so let's move on and start developing these components in the next lecture.