In the last lecture, we finished a set up of our project,
now I want to start developing the app. For that
I'll first of all run npm start to start this development server so that we can see the app run on
http://localhost:3000. Make sure you're saving all files so that you don't get the compilation errors.
I got
and with that, you will basically not see anything because we emptied the app.js file,
it's just having an empty div,
obviously we don't see content.
Now let's start implementing the components we sketched out in the previous lectures and there are actually
a couple of components we need
but we can kind of separate our project into two branches.
Well overall these branches we got a layout component but below that, we basically have navigation related
components, like the toolbar and the side drawer and we have the meat of our application, the burger builder.
Now I'd say let's start with the burger builder then, that's probably the more fun part
to start with.
Now for that, I first of all will create that layout component though which will kind of be a wrapper
implementing the toolbar and the burger builder then and later in this course once we add routing and
more pages to our application, we will take advantage of this layout where the toolbar will always be
there but where we will then switch the page which is rendered in the content area of the layout so
to say. Now we could simply turn the app.js file into a layout because it basically is the root component
of our application and that would be a perfectly fine approach,
I will still create a separate component for that though to have a component entirely focusing on the
layout. Now for that, I'll create a new sub-folder in the source folder and I will name it components,
I will create a second sub-folder which I'll name containers.
Now remember, containers are stateful components, so components created with the class keyword or functional
components using useState and components going into the components folder are dumb or presentational
components that don't manage state,
no matter if they were created as a class but don't use the state or if they are functional components
that aren't using hooks.
Now I will create the layout in the components folder because right now, I don't need to manage any
state there.
So in components, I'll create a sub-folder which I'll name Layout with a capital L and in layout, I will
create the layout.js file so that we have this layout component placed in that folder. That is
a typical project setup you use in React, having a components and a containers folder. Other folders you
often see are an assets folder, we will use this later once we add a logo and you might also have a folder
for the Redux store and so on,
we haven't even learned about that,
we will add it once we got that,
so back to the layout then. There I will create a normal functional component and store it in a constant
named layout and there this is my function and now let's have a look at how this function should look
like or how the JSX exported by the function should look like. There
I basically want to have two areas you could say, I'll have a div, for now just a placeholder which will
hold my toolbar, my side drawer and probably for the side drawer, also a backdrop.
So we will need to replace this div with three components later on,
we also did plan this in the previous lectures. Below
this part, we'll have a main area
and this is the normal main element provided by HTML and there,
I want to output the component we wrap with this layout, so I will use props children and for that of
course, I need to import props or not import it, excuse me, get it as an argument.
Now this allows us to simply use this layout component as a wrapper around the core content component
we want to render to the screen.
Now here, we get an error in the IDE because one important thing is missing, the import of the React
package or the React object I should say from the React package,
once we added this, we still see a error because we have adjacent JSX elements.
Now I taught you that there are basically two solutions to that,
do you remember them? Well for one, we could return an array here instead of JSX which is sitting next
to each other,
if we return an array and give each item a key, we are allowed to kind of return adjacent elements.
The alternative is to create such an auxiliary higher order component which I showed you in the last
course module.
It serves only one purpose,
wrapping something and immediately outputting it but hence fulfilling the requirement of having a wrapping
component.
I will use this,
we also have of course the third option of wrapping everything in a div here or another element but
I don't need that div or any other element,
actually I want to have adjacent elements,
that is why I will go with the higher order component approach and create such a utility auxiliary component.
For that,
I'll create a new folder in the source folder, hoc for higher order component and there I will create an
aux.js file.
Now the auxiliary component is really really simple,
it's a functional component where I also won't manage any state with hooks and I will name it aux
and here I just get props as an input and I return props children, nothing else,
no wrapping element.
We don't even have any JSX in this file which is also why we don't have to import React from React.
I will then export aux as the default in this file and save the file
and now back in the layout file, I can import Aux with a capital A like for all custom components we
want to use from and now we have to move up until we are at the source folder level and there from
the hoc folder from the aux file, without .js at the end because keep in mind, our build workflow
will add this file extension for Javascript files automatically. And now I can wrap everything here
with this auxiliary component, so that we now fulfill the requirement of having a wrapping root element.
Finally let me export this layout function as the default for this file and now with that, we can use
it in the app.js file in our root component.
Now granted, you could also go to the index file, import layout here and simply render the layout function
as the root component and
that's basically the same solution as making the app.js file the root component.
You could absolutely do that and that wouldn't be wrong,
it's just my personal decision to have this root component in case I should ever decide to restructure
the app, add some state to my root component, maybe conditionally render different layouts or do anything
like that. For the app as it is,
we could definitely turn the app component itself into the layout. Now
enough talk about that, let's import our layout component then with a capital L, from and now we have
to go into the components folder, into the layout folder and there to the layout.js file and now we
can simply render layout
and this should now not be a self-closing component because the idea behind the whole layout is that
I can wrap another component with it.
For now let's simply wrap a paragraph just to see if this is working, if we are correctly passing this
to layout but later, we will of course wrap a real component, the page we actually want to display with it.
So make sure all files are saved and then head over to your http://localhost:3000 page.
Make sure your development server is running and there you should see our placeholder for the toolbar,
for the side drawer, the backdrop and so on and you also see the test paragraph I just added.
If you inspect everything, you will notice that we don't use our open sans font though because we haven't
added it, so let's fix this too.
Let's go to index.css, we did add the import to the public folder,
so here we simply happen to add open sans like this as our main font and use sans-serif as a backup
font and now you see, the font changed and in the elements tab,
you also see that now it is applied.
With that, we get the roof of our application finished for now,
there is of course a lot of work left regarding the navigation here, the toolbar and everything but since
we don't have multiple pages right now, we don't need to take care about the navigation right now. So
let's instead focus on the core functionality of our application, the burger builder. We'll start implementing
that in the next lectures.