In the last lecture, we executed switchNameHandler upon a click,
now we want to manipulate the state up on the click. So I'll comment out this console log statement and we
could simply do this
state, reaching out to this state property here
and as I mentioned, this will only work when using this syntax
otherwise this here will not refer to the class and will therefore not be able to reach that state property
but here it will work.
So this state persons, then maybe access person 1 and set the name to Maximilian,
my full name.
Let's save this and let's see what happens if we execute this code.
We already get a warning here but let's ignore it for now and let's click switch name,
nothing changes, we still see Max here.
Well as I said, we do get a warning about this,
we shouldn't mutate which means change the state directly like this, React will not recognize that and
it will not pick up this change,
so don't do this.
Instead use a special method React gives you, you also access this with this and then it's set state.
We haven't defined this method but remember that we extend component and this is made available by the
React library and the component object happens to have a set state method.
This is a method which allows us to update this special state property here and it will then ensure
that React gets to know about this update and updates the DOM. set state takes an object as an argument
and it will merge whatever we define here with our existing state.
So if I here set persons to an updated array, it will merge this with existing data,
so if we had some other state here which is some other value, then this would not get touched
even if we only update persons. Not clear what I mean,
let me show you.
I'm copying persons and I'm basically adding this as a property in the object I'm about to use as my update
here.
So I'm saying this set state and set state takes this new object where I update my persons, where I
only change the first person or maybe also let's change Stephanie, let's change her age to 27.
Now what it will do, what React will do for us is it will look at our state and see which part of it we're
overwriting, we're changing, persons,
it will not discard other state but it will simply merge the old state with the new one. We'll overwrite
persons
since we clearly define a new version of persons here but we'll leave other state untouched because we're
not saying anything about it here and it will not discard it
which of course is a good thing, you don't want to have to update everything about your state whenever
you want to change
only a tiny piece about it.
So with that, let's now see what happens if we save this file. If we save it now and reload the app and
I click switch name,
watch Max and watch 26 years old down there. You see that, it's Maximilian and 27 years. Now the
DOM was updated because React recognized that the state of our application changes and this really is
a special thing,
there aren't many things which lead React to update the DOM.
There actually only are two, changing state and what else? You could already see it in action,
props.
We change state,
that's nice
but keep in mind what we actually output for each person is defined in this person component
and there we don't useState and as I said, we could use it with React hooks and I'll introduce you to
React hooks right after this lecture here
but for now we're not using state in here but in our class-based component instead. Here
we use props and that's the other thing React watches out for. If state changes or props changes,
it basically analyzes the code it already rendered to the DOM and the code it would now render if it
were to re-render everything and then it updates the existing DOM in all the places where it needs to
update it to reflect your new state
and props. New state in app.js, new props in person.js.