In a previous lecture we learned about state and most importantly, how we manipulate it with set state,
this set state.
Now that's a feature only available in class-based components, so components you construct by using the
class keyword which extend component which is imported from React.
Now prior to React version 16.8, this was the only way of managing state in React applications
and to say this right away,
it is the way we'll use throughout this course and I'll come back to why in a second.
Now since React 16.8, there also is a way for us to manage state in functional components with a
feature called React hooks.
Now I'll show you this feature here already and actually in this course, there are two complete modules
on React hooks, one which teaches them from the ground up and one that also then converts the entire
course project to use React hooks and the reasons why we need to convert
that is because for this course, I'll stick to the setup, the traditional setup where you use class-based
components for managing state, even though
now since React 16.8 we could use functional components for everything.
Now why do I stick to this setup?
Well it has been the only way in the past and if you're joining a company working on a React team, you
will work with this syntax because it is the established syntax and all projects will be written like
this because it was the only way of creating components in the past.
This new way we're using these React hooks is totally optional and it's not even sure if this will be
the main way of creating components in the future and therefore in this course, you'll simply learn both
and we'll use this established way here which is the default way of creating components in React and
we'll use this throughout the course
and I will introduce hooks as they make sense,
so here and also in later module and then we'll have these entire modules I already mentioned on React
hooks where you learn all about them so that once you've finish this course, you really are a React expert
in whichever way you want to look at it, you will know all the different ways and their advantages of
using React, making it possible for you to join any React job you want.
So with that, let me show you what this React hooks feature looks like and React
hooks is really just the name of it,
it's basically a collection of functions exposed to you by React which you can use in functional components
and therefore, we'll have to convert this component here into a functional one.
For that I'll create a constant named app and this will be a function that gets props and then has a
function body,
so just as we have it here in person.js, there we also created our component like that. So in here, we
now no longer have state or switchNameHandler, so I'll cut that and temporarily add it here at the bottom
so that we can later reuse that logic. We should export default app with a lowercase A because I renamed
my constant to to have a lowercase A, if you named it with an uppercase of course you don't need to
change this and then in your function body, you have no render method, you just return JSX. Basically
as you learned it for functional components,
this is a normal functional component but now you can use this React hooks feature or one of the React
hooks because React 16.8 and therefore you should check your package.json file whether
your project does use React 16.8, if not update the version and rerun npm install so you
do. So your React 16.8 or higher project now is able to use hooks and you do use them by
importing them from React, so instead of component which we don't need here anymore because we're not
extending it anymore, you can import use, all these hooks start with the use keyword and you see there
are a couple of hooks, state. useState is the most important React hook and I'll introduce other
hooks throughout this course but useState is the hook that allows us to manage state in a functional
component.
Now how do we use it?
Well you call it like a function, like this and then to useState, you pass your initial state.
So for that, we can copy that object we previously set up on our state property,
so here I'll pass that into useState, like that.
Now this uses this hook but what does it actually do?
useState returns an array with exactly two elements and always two elements, that's important.
So we can store this in let's say a state array constant.
Now the first element we get back will always be our current state,
so initially that object and whenever we change it,
well the updated state. The second element in state array will always be a function that allows us to
update this state, such that React is aware of it and will re-render this component which is of course
the idea and which is what also happens with this set state in class-based components. So we can also
use a more modern Javascript feature called array destructuring which works by adding square brackets
on the left side of the equal sign here and this allows you to pull elements out of the array you get
back from the right side of the equal sign,
so of this function call.
So in here you can give these elements any name you want and therefore I'll name the first one here
persons state for example, again
that name is totally up to you
and the second element will be a function that allows you to set that state, so I'll name it setPersons, you
can also name it set person state, whatever you want,
so maybe let's set persons state to be really clear what this does.
So now we have these two things, persons state gives you access to this object,
so therefore in all the places where we previously used this state, we now replace this state in all
these places with persons state because this state doesn't exist anymore,
it only exists in class-based React components and we have no such class-based React component here
anymore,
it's a functional component.
So this acceses the persons data, set persons state allows us to set a new state and for this, we
can re-add that switchNameHandler to our component
but how do we add a method, as this was before, to a functional component? Well turns out you can have
functions inside functions, not just in React but in Javascript in general
and therefore here, we can add a new function stored in a constant maybe which is my old switchNameHandler,
I just copied that code.
So now I have that switchNameHandler constant which holds this function code here and this is perfectly
fine Javascript code, you can have a function definition inside of a function. Looks strange and you typically
don't use it too often but for React hooks, you use that and it is fine because now you have a functional
component that can manage state and that can have other functions that do something for example upon
a click
and that's exactly what I do here. On click
we previously called this switchNameHandler,
well the this keyword is now wrong because we are not inside of a class anymore,
instead it's just switchNameHandler, referring to this constant here. Still without parentheses because
I don't want to execute it immediately but only when this click occurs and then this function will execute
and now we won't call set state anymore because this function also doesn't exist anymore,
instead of this set state, it's now just set persons state and we pass our new state object into there.
And with that if you save it, with your development server still up and running, this is the app and
this looks still good
which already means that useState generally works, otherwise would not be able to extract data from
our persons state down there.
So if I now press switch name, watch Max here, it's Maximilian.
So extracting the state and updating the state and re-rendering the component upon a state change all
works.
There is one important difference to the state in a class-based component though, it generally looks
like it works the same but it doesn't. Let me console log persons state here so that we can see what's
inside.
If I save this, this app reloads,
so here we have Max and on Maximilian and this is what's in our state, right?
It's an object with other state because we're setting this as well to demonstrate that this doesn't
get overwritten and persons and if I clicks switch name, we get the new state and oh, other state is missing
and that is super important. When you're using React hooks,
your function here which you get as the second element in that array does not merge whatever you pass
to it with the old state,
instead it replaces the old state with it
and this is super important because this means that whenever you're updating the state like this, you
have to manually make sure you include all old state data.
Here for example by manually adding the other state property and then you have to access the persons
state here and access other state and this will just make sure that we copy in the old,
in this case untouched other state, of course you could change it here as well
and when you are doing that, now if I click switch name, other state is still there.
Now this is one way of doing it but the more elegant way is actually to not manually merge your states
but instead use useState multiple times, whereas in class-based components, you only have one state property
and this set state automatically merges changes with the old state
to not discard any state, here you can have multiple useState calls.
So we can call
useState again and there if we wanted to manage our other state, we could pass in our other state, some
other value object here or if all we want to manage is a string,
we could also just pass in that string as a default value,
it doesn't have to be an object.
It could be an object as it is here,
it could also just be a string, a number, an array, a boolean, whatever your app needs and you can have
as many useState calls as you want.
And therefore now if I log my person state and then here, I also extract that into two variables with the
help of array destructuring, that could be my other state and set other state.
So now if I log persons state and other state and I'm never using set other state because I don't want
to set it anywhere,
now if I log both here with two useState calls, back in the app you see initially we got our person
state which still has its own other state so let's remove that.
So again we load,
so now we have the persons state which is just this object and then we have our some other state here,
some other value
and if I switch name, we updated persons and we still have some other value because that state is not
touched by our call to set persons state which only interacts with that first useState result.
So multiple useState with different state slices
so to say, that is how you manage state in a functional component with React hooks.
You don't have one big state object, though you could and you could manually merge it if you prefer that
but instead, you have multiple separated state slices.
This is the useState hook and this is a glimpse at React hooks in general and this is the most important
React hook.
To summarize it, React hooks is all about these use something functions with useState being the most
important, that allow you to add functionality to functional components, like here useState allows us
to add state management to functional components.
So if you are using React hooks only
and again, I will teach you all these important hooks throughout this course,
you don't need to use class-based components. Still as I mentioned, in this course
I will use class-based components because that's the established way,
this is the way you will need it in any job you're starting
and therefore if you want to become a React developer, you absolutely have to know that name.
Still, you'll also learn this React hook syntax along the way and to mention it again,
there are two complete modules toward the end of this course where I in one module walk through all
the important React hooks so that you have them all in one place and in the other module,
I'll take that React project, this complete course project we'll eventually build in this course and convert
this to use React hooks only, so you are well-prepared for whichever project you are diving into.
So this was a nice excursion here, attached you find a rollback to the class-based approach and you also
find this code here, so that you have this for reference
but take that rollback, that class-based approach to continue because that is the approach with which
we'll continue throughout this course and which we'll use throughout this course.