In the last lectures, we learned a lot about state and props and you learned that every component receives
props and that since React 16.8, you can also manage state in every component.
Prior to that version, you could only manage state in class-based components.
Now either way,
no matter if you're creating a component with the class keyword or as a functional component, if you
are managing state in it, either with the state property and this set state or with the React useState
hook,
no matter which of the approaches you're using, you can differentiate your components in stateful and
stateless components. A stateful component is a component that manages state, no matter if it's using
the useState hook or a class-based approach with the state property. A component like the person.js file, so
this person component is a stateless component because it has no internal state management and it
is a good practice to create as many of these stateless components, also called dumb because they have
no internal logic or presentational components because they present something, they output content, they
only get external data and output it in a structured way,
it is a good practice to use as many of these stateless, dumb, presentational components as possible in
your application.
The stateful components,
so either class-based with state or functional with useState are also called smart components or container
components because they contain the state of your application, of these components,
you only want to have a couple.
Well of course that depends on the size of your app,
if you have an app with thousands of components, you'll also have multiple containers, so stateful components.
But the idea is that you restrict yourself to a setup where you have way more functional presentational
components than stateful components.
Now why?
Because this makes your app easier to maintain and manage.
You have a clear flow of data and it's very clear where your main logic sits and where your data changes
and then is distributed to the rest of your app.
So if anyone, including yourself, ever needs to change something about the app, it's clear where to make
that change.
If every component in your app manages its own state, you quickly end up with spaghetti code where everyone
is doing everything and that can make your app very hard to reuse, to maintain and so on. So have as many
pure functional presentational components as possible and only use state
no matter how in a few selected components and keep these terms in mind because you will hear me say
container or stateful or smart component for the stateful components in this course and you'll
also hear me say presentational, stateless or dumb component which means such components, of which you
should have more than stateful components.