So let's go through all these steps which are outlined in the rapture.
Last fall I will actually leave this list here.
As you can see a normal order list so that we can always call ems at our tasks and the first task is
to create two new components user input and user output.
So in the source folder which is where we write our re-act code alternate to a new folder user input
and next to it user output and it shows these names because these should be the component names.
And as you learned it is a good practice to name the folders and files according to what you want to
name your component.
So inside the user input folder all I'm going to create a user input js file inside user output it's
to user output dodgiest file.
So if that already solved task number one we create a T components.
And of course these components aren't that useful.
And actually we only created files these aren't really components.
Now we should add something there to return some GSX code in the components.
And for today we need to create real components to begin with.
I'm going to start with the user input and you'll learn that you basically have two different ways of
creating a component extending the component object provided by react or simply creating a function.
You also learned that you should try to use a function as often as possible to have basically representational
only component which just returns some GSX in the end and you mostly need to extend the component if
you want to manipulate state.
I want to manipulate state in never user input nor the user output component so I'll create functions
in both of them.
I'll create a user it function camel case notation to follow the convention and this will simply be
stored in this constant user input.
It's a ESX arrow function as you learned.
And you also learned one other important thing which can easily be forgotten.
You need to import re-act from react in any component you create does as required because the J is X
code you return isn't the end Colewort it to react create element speaking or returning something here.
I want to return something.
And if we have a look at our assignment we should return an input element in there.
So let's just do that.
No need to wrap it in a def we can just return an input maybe of type text just like that.
And of course to be able to use this component I need to export it and I will simply define default
export of this file to beat it in user input constant which simply is my function which returns my GSX.
That's the user input.
Let's save this file.
Let's now work on the user output.
And there we should return two paragraphs.
For now with any text of your choice.
So again I will create a constant which I'll name user output which will hold a reference or which will
store this function I should say as before we need to import re-act from react to prevent errors.
And then I want to return something and here I will return a wrapping.
Def because I want to have multiple elements sit next to each other and Wild's react 16 actually will
support returning a raise.
It is still a good practice actually required to wrap multiple elements sitting next to each other without
them being in an array like this.
So here we'll have a def wrapping my component and now in there I want to have two paragraphs so let
me quickly create bouffe and duplicated.
And here I will output some random text and some more random text with that let's safe this fall too.
And now we need to use these components.
We right now completed the second task.
Now we should output multiple user output components in our app component.
And actually why don't we also output the user input component already.
So in Apter genius I went to import my new components so import user input and as I mentioned earlier
this name is up to you but you should use your component name there and start with a capital character
to not confuse react.
So import that from dot slash user input and there the user input js file where you can omit default
extension since it is a javascript file.
The same for the user output.
Import user output from Dart's slash user output and their user output file without the extension.
Now I'll leave the instructions in there but below my ordered list I actually will now add my user input
a self-closing tech and also my user output and number is self-closing tag and all duplicators twice
to have three user outputs.
Let's save DHHS file and let's see I now get an error or export default not found in user output.
This actually makes sense because I forgot to add my export you are of course having the function to
use the output file like this isn't worth anything to be able to access it from a number of fault.
I need to export it.
In this case doing it with the default export of this file.
Now with that being saved it does work.
We see the input and then we see three times our user output component.
So is this task number free solved.
Now we want to add something else and leave the world of static content.
We want to pass a user name to the user output component while props.
Well you'll learn how to do that.
We can simply add a user name property may maybe written like that written like that.
What ever you like to name is totally up to you.
Could also be a user name.
It's your choice after all.
So use user name here here I will simply pass max and you could pass different user names for different
components.
Now I will actually pass the same but as you learned over the last lectures you can of course pass different
data and that is a common pattern to do.
Typically your components should rendered the same jazz X but with dynamic counted here I'll take the
same user name.
We're going to overwrite this with the state soon anyways.
And of course passing it like this is only one step.
We want to output it to safety mapped out js file and let's move on to the user output file.
There we know that we can get access to the prop's passed in by react by accepting an argument in that
function and then output it.
And now let's add something to the paragraphs here.
Now we don't get any instructions where to add water or what to do with that.
Simply that we should display the user name in the user output.
So why don't we simply say user name colon and then you'll learn how to pass or to output dynamic content.
Single curly braces between a single curly braces opening and closing you access props user name and
make sure that the name you use here and the casing you use here matches its name and casing of your
attribute here.
And one important information in normal h t m l d attributes are case insensitive.
Sell this as a normal HTML attribute.
Wouldn't work but keep in mind we're not using normal age HTML here.
This is just syntactic sugar so we can use case sensitive names.
So user output were outputting this here.
Now let's save this.
And we should see user name Max.
Max and Max free times or however often you used your user output component.
So this is Task Force solved.
The next task is to actually manage to username why a state and pass it why a state to our component.
Now nothing easier than that.
You learned how to add and you state.
You also learned that you can't access state a function components or components written as a function.
Now of course you could convert that into a component which extends component object provided by react
but you also learn that it's a good thing to have many components in this function for him and manage
to state in a few central places in your app so-called containers.
Now we have such a container already aperture as is a normal week component but since it extends the
component object provided by re-act that it effectively is such a container.
But mind container's just how you name it.
It's not a special object you have to create or inherit from.
So we have a component which extends component and that is the app dot Jr's file or the component in
that file.
Therefore we can add state here and you learned that state is just a property of your class justice
rendered as a method.
We can also add our state property here and state just be a javascript object in our case here.
I will set up a user named property and I'll write it all lowercase just to have a distinction to the
prop you could use it in the camel case notation.
Nothing wrong with that.
And I'll name it.
Super Max here sounds like a good user name for me.
Now with that I want to pass that user name and the state to my props.
So down there where I use my user output I'll now pass something dynamic.
This state username.
All lowercase since this is how I define user name there.
And a lecturer will place all three prompts with it though it wouldn't need to do that.
I could also leave one to be hardcoded.
Well maybe you would do that.
It's totally up to you.
So that if we save us and we go back to the application we see super max Super Max Max.
So we're successfully using the state.
We're not really using it to updated though.
We're not able to change it yet.
We'll start with this in Task 6 though we add a method to manipulate the steady state and event handler
method to be precise.
Now it still is a regular method the event handler addition is only important to keep in mind for naming
the method according to the convention.
So here this should be triggered whenever we type something into the input in the user input component.
So what would be a fitting name for that method.
Maybe simply input changed handler or something like user name change handler whatever you like now
will define this as a property which holds a function ESX arrow function effectively turning this into
a method.
Now if you closely watched you might also have recognized that to render all as a method but uses a
different syntax you can use both syntaxes either does property which holds a function syntax here or
does syntax which looks more like methods are written in other languages.
There is one important difference though.
If you plan on using this keyword inside the method as we do plan to do here you should use this syntax
where you have a property and assign a function because this will basically encapsulate that this keyword
to still refer to the class which you want to do to get access to the state and so on with a method
defined like this.
Generally this side of it will still refer to the class as you can clearly see down here.
But if you execute it as an event listener as planted you for a user name changed handler.
This would no longer refer to the class simply due to the way how javascript works when executing code
at runtime.
So therefore we should use this syntax for our event handlers for our methods.
It doesn't really matter and you might use this syntax or this syntax.
Both will work there.
So enough of the talking about the syntax.
Let's see what we should do with it.
We should add a method to manipulate a state and basically change the state based on the input we get.
Now we know that we will receive an event here because we plan on using this as an event listener method.
So here I can call this set stage to manipulate the state and that's important.
Keep in mind to call sets state and don't directly manipulate to state.
This will not work and is strictly wrong said state provided by the component object by re-act will
merge whatever you pass your with your existing state safely override that or adjust it and inform re-act
that the state was changed and that it should check if it needs to update the dawn.
So here we want to set username.
Actually the only property we have in our state to event target value.
As you know event target will refer to the element d event occurred on and value is a valid property
we may access.
Since we know that event target will be an input element which has a value property containing the value
the user entered.
This alone will update the state and will inform re-act that the state changed.
It will then check if it needs to change.
This part here does code and actually it doesn't because we never output anything from the state here
but we do pass it as props to the user output component and it will check all of its child elements
too for user input as well.
Right now at least determined that it doesn't need to update it.
But for user outputted knows did we get props and if props change which they do because we change the
state which we send while props.
It will rerun this part here.
This is how it will work behind the scenes though I will have a whole module where I dive deeper into
what happens except the behind the scenes.
In case you are interested in that.
So for now we get a method which we can call which would update the state.
Of course we need to call it though we added the method to manipulate the state.
Now we should past event handler method reference to the user input component and blind to the input
and change event there so on user input.
Maybe we should pass a property name changed and the name is totally up to you.
This is no reserved word.
It's just a prop defined by you and there I will pass is user name changed handler.
Without parentheses don't add parentheses.
You don't want to be executed here you just want to pass a reference to this method.
In the user input method we now also receive props years so let's accept them as an argument and on
the input we now listen to the onchange event which is provided by react and there I want to pass the
props changed property that the property would just set up here.
And this refers to that event handler.
So by passing a reference to that property we actually pass a reference to the event handler.
So this event were dismantled excuse me will get executed whenever the onchange event occurs.
Also don't add parentheses here you don't want to execute this right at the time this gets rendered
to the dawn.
But at the point of time this event occurs it will automatically past event object to our event handler.
As you.
Now with that that's saved the user input component and make sure all the other files are safe too.
And now let's see if this actually works.
We already completed this task where we ensured dead the input entry but the user overrides the old
username.
We do this here with set state make sure that NPM start is running in the project and there after simply
entering something here like test and you'll see that all the components were I did pass state as a
user name or state username as the user name it will override it.
It won't.
Oh right down here because Max there is simply hard coded.
Now let's all those that have two way binding so that when we load the application we also actually
see our current username supermax India and put field instead of an empty input.
Now for that in the user input here I simply have to bind the value property to something I need to
pass on as props for Daddles simply restructured over multiple lines just to make it easier to read
and then pass props.
And there may be simply value.
You could choose any other name though so maybe also current name to have a clear distinction to disvalue
which is a research name because it's in a default age female element.
Now let's use that current name Propp which I defined here in actually yes.
And let's pass it here.
Current name that's all split this over multiple lines to make it easier to learn to read.
And there the current name of course is to current user name stored in the state just like we pass it
to user output on the different property there.
So let's save this.
And as it reloads we see super max and we can start changing it.
If you open the developer tools you'll see that this time we don't get a warning in the console because
unlike tudy lectures prior to the assignment here we only use this to be binding in cases where we do
actually provide a change handler and the value with that we are almost done.
The missing piece is the styling.
And here you are totally free to use whichever styling you want.
Now I will use two different approaches for the user input where I don't have a wrapping element.
I will set up some inline styles to make sure that the styling only gets applied to this input and not
to any input I might have in my application.
Even though I don't have one here so here's style is a javascript object and I will simply give my input
a border which is let's say two pixels wide solid and red.
And I assign it by using the default style property which is known on this H M L or I should say.
J.S. X element and I assign my style variable up appear as a value and the name is totally up to you.
You could also name this input style.
To not confuse it with the property or attribute you are assigning it to.
So that is inline styles being used in user input as you learned the advantages.
This is now really scoped to dis input only.
If I were to use the input anywhere else in my application this style would not get applied because
in the end we apply it as an inline style for the user output of follow a different approach.
I'll add a C S S for user output and I'll add a user output as class.
Their eyes simply want to have a width of let's say 60 percent.
I want to have the padding of 16 pixels and a margin of 16 pixels.
I want to have a border of two pixels solid and black and a background color of this gray and I want
to set text aligned to center maybe and you can choose any style you want.
Now just by doing that we're not going to see any styling at all.
We have to go to the component we want a style and first of all import our style sheet.
We're not importing anything from there.
We just import the overall sheet by passing it as relative path with file extension and web spec the
build tool getting use behind the scenes will automatically take care of it and include it correctly
in our page.
This alone still will install thing because all we do in there is we define this user output CSSA class.
So we should use this class then we can do this year on this wrapping death.
They're also the class name not to something dynamic but to a hard coded string user output.
The class I defined in here now important does all that shows why wrapping your component in one root
element makes a lot of sense and it's not just an annoying requirement.
It makes it easy to assign a style to your component.
No make sure all the files you edited are saved.
You have no dots on any of these files.
And now let's go back and here indeed we see our style components with the style sheet and the input
with the inline style with the red border and of course it still works as before.
Now with our custom styling which you might be able to improve from lay out the science perspective
but from a learning perspective I'd say you learned a lot about the bass syntax of react.
Now let's continue and dive deeper into what you can do especially how we can render a content dynamically
or conditionally I should say depending on some conditions or how we can output lists of data.