In the last lecture I highlighted why we want to set up a project which gives us some additional features
which make our life as a developer easier now as I also mentioned there is a tool which creates such
a project for us.
It's called Create react app and you can simply google for it to find a link to its official github
repository.
As I said it's maintained by basically Facebook or a community around Facebook so it's officially recommended
tool for creating react projects on that github page.
You will find installation instructions and a detailed explanation about what it does and how it works.
Feel free to read it but of course you're also going to learn all about that throughout this course.
So let's start with the installation.
We install it globally with NPM and NPM as simply nodes package manager a tool you automatically get
when installing node J.S. which makes it easy to manage third party packages.
Other javascript packages in the end and create reactive is just such a package to use NPM.
You need to install node J.S. which you can download and install from node J.S. dot org.
Now there you should pick the latest version 8 dot 5.
In my case here.
But if you're facing any issues with that all to try out where's the six study eleven or what average
long term support version is in your case when you're viewing this page now.
No worries we're not going to write any note J.S. code here.
You don't need to know.
Note J.S. we only need it to use its package manager and also for this development server which will
be spun up for us automatically.
So simply click these buttons download and no chance and it will open up installer through which you
can walk.
Once you did finished installation you should be able to run the NPM command here on your machine.
So let's do this together in the next step.
Now to use d create react app tool use simply open up a terminal or a command prompt on your machine
and then there you run npm install and that's what you need node James for.
It gives you that NPM tool npm install create dash react dash app and then important add dash G after
this to install it globally on your machine so that you can use this command from anywhere on your machine.
Now on windows you can simply hit enter on Mac and Linux you might need to add sudo in front of this.
If you hit enter and get a permission error to get the right permissions after you did hit Enter you're
probably prompt to enter your password and you might want to enter correctly the first time.
Unlike I did but after all that create react app should be installed.
Now you can use that command to create a new project and you do so by running create react app and then
the name of your project and off the folder into which it will be installed.
Now important before you run this command navigate into the powerful your system where you want to create
that new folder.
So here I'm on the desktop but with the help of S.D. you can of course navigate into a different path
to store your project there then run create react app and then the name of your project which could
be my app or react dash complete guide for example because that is what this course is about.
Now one important note to get the exact same folder structure as I have it since this changes over time
a bit and you follow along perfectly.
You have to add something to this command so don't hit enter yet instead add a whitespace a blank and
then add dash dash scripts.
Werman So this is all one and the same command even though it's split in two lines here on my machine
but it's one command so dash dash scripts dash where John and then a whitespace then one dot one dot
five.
Now this does not impact the question of react.
You're using you are using the latest version of react no worries.
This simply impacts the structure of the project.
We will change that structure for the course any.
But to start with the same well starting point.
Use this command simply hit enter their offer and a new project will be created for you.
So this will now create a new folder and set everything up for you.
There you can ignore all the warnings you might be getting here.
Everything will be fine no worries.
So let's wait for this command to finish.
Now and once this is finished you'll see a bunch of commands you can run.
Now here you see ya and start ya and build.
That is because I have installed yarn which is an alternative to NPM on my machine queue.
You will all will who run these commands with NPM run start NPM run build and so on.
So first of all though you have to navigate into the newly created folder.
So with S.D. react that complete dash guide if you named the project like I did here and then in there
you can run NPM start to start your project and what this means is it starts a development server which
opens a new tab in the browser or at least should open that tab in case it does and you can manually
open a browser tab and visit local host Colon Free thousand there.
And this is a first project first demo app that well is created for you which we can now edit this process
here.
The NPM start process should be kept on running don't quit it.
You can always quit it by hitting control and see but if you quit it it will stop watching your files.
And as long as it keeps running on the other end it is watching your files and what does this mean.
It means that whenever you change something in code this page will automate you reload and reflect the
latest changes which is awesome.
So as soon as you're done developing you can quit this as long as you are developing keep this process
running.
Now with that process running again and that application running here on local host three thousand let's
have a look at the folder that was created and all the files we find in there.
In the next lecture.