Attached to this lecture here, you'll find the starting project
you can see here, I just started it with npm start,
it uses create React project.
I didn't
edit it to use CSS modules, instead I just import CSS files so that they affect the project globally
but that doesn't pose an issue here and I've got a couple of containers or one container and a couple
of components.
As you can see at the example of the full post component here, which is responsible for rendering this
part here,
now I do have class based components here as components because I will add some state and lifecycle
methods here,
now of course you could theoretically also convert these to functional components and use hooks there,
useState and useEffect but as for the rest of this main course here, I'll stay to the class-based syntax
and to learn all about hooks, I got these separate modules.
Still, I only have one component which will distribute some properties down to other components,
this is the root page you could say which should render some posts at the top, then a full post with
some details about a post we clicked on and the area for creating a new post,
you can see all these features here on that page.
Now I do have some dummy content here because I want to load that post data from a server and
for that
we're not going to use a real server,
we will do that though in the next module when we apply some HTTP functionality to our course project
but here, I will use JSONPlaceholder which you can find at jsonplaceholder.typeicode.com
which simply is a back-end, a RESTful API back-end which you typically use
as I explained in the last lecture where you can send requests to to fetch some dummy data or to simulate
storing some dummy data there, though you won't actually store something on that server of course, it's
just faking some data
but exactly what we need for learning how to send HTTP requests.
For example, you can send a request to that URL here, a get request and you will get an array of Javascript
objects of dummy posts
and this actually is what I want to start with.
So we will start with that in the next lecture but we of course need some way of sending these Ajax
requests
and here you have basically two options, Javascript of course has the XML HTTP request object, this object
here.
With that you can construct your own Ajax requests and send them to a specific URL and handle the
response.
Nothing wrong with that since React is just about writing Javascript everywhere, you can of course use
all the Javascript features including XML HTTP request. But writing and configuring requests with that
object manually is quite cumbersome, so the second option is to use a package, a third-party library which
makes that easier
and for that I recommend using axios. Axios
is a third-party Javascript library which you can add to any Javascript project,
it's not connected to React at all but of course it fits nicely into Raect because it's Javascript
and the axios page here on Github is a good starting point to learn more about this package.
I will of course walk you through some of its core features in this module though but again, this is
not something strongly connect to React,
axios can be used in any Javascript code. So let's install axios in this lecture already and then get started
using it in the next lecture. To install axios,
I will quit my development server with control c and then run npm install axios --save to also
store an entry in the package.json file. This will download and store the package
and with that we can start using it in the next lecture to fetch some posts.
So let me restart the development server with npm start and I'll then see you in the next lecture to download
some posts and output them there.