In the last lecture, we made sure that we show a spinner, a loader to the user whilst the request is on
its way.
That's of course a good thing to do, it improves our user experience because the user clearly sees that
something is happening.
It's also an improvement to the user experience
if we show error messages in case something fails
and here again, there are different places to where you could show such an error message,
I simply want to set up some global error handler which shows a modal with the error message but doesn't
use the modal here because I don't want to be stuck to this container, to the burger builder container.
I want to have a flexible way of showing an error, no matter which component, in which container it occurs,
so therefore my modal is going to get added to a higher level in the application and I want to have
a higher level of the application, so some higher component
than this burger builder container where I catch errors and where I then make sure that my error modal
is displayed.
Now where can we set this up,
how can we control this?
I simply want to create a higher order component with which I can wrap the burger builder or which I'll
actually use in that second way I showed you for using higher order components so that we can simply
wrap any component which should have this error modal with it and can conveniently add the error handling
functionality to it.
So for this, I'm going to create my new higher order component in a folder which I'll name
withErrorHandler, I am using this syntax withErrorHandler because I want to use this second way of
creating a higher order component which will be used here on the export and not used as JSX code.
So in there, I'll add a witherrorhandler.js file and this file here
now will take the following form,
it will be a function, withErrorHandler, and this should be a function which takes the wrapped component
as an input and which then returns a function which receives props
and of course simply returns some JSX including the wrapped component,
so for that we need to import React from React. And now here,
I of course want to return the wrapped component and distribute any props
this component might receive on it because I don't know these props but I definitely don't want to lose
them,
I then want to export this withErrorHandler function as the default but now I also want to use my
or add my error modal.
So for that, I need to import two things, the modal component of course from the components UI modal
folder and there, the modal.js file and since I want to place it next to it, I need the aux component
from the aux folder in the hoc folder.
So now I can wrap it all with aux like this and add the modal next to it,
don't use a self-closing tag here because in the modal of course I want to output something. For now
I'll just say something didn't work,
just like that.
Now we can finetune this but this is what I want to show right now,
now let's see if this works.
If we save this, we now have our higher order component,
let's now use this on the burger builder.
There
I will import it at the top,
so withErrorHandler starting with a lowercase character because we're not going to use it in JSX
and now I'll navigate to my hoc folder and there to the withErrorHandler folder and witherrorhandler.js
file of course and then take that withErrorHandler function we're importing and wrap the burger
boulder with it, like this.
Now with this if we go back to the withErrorHandler function and set show like this, so to true simply
on the modal, if we save this and go back, we should always see something didn't work.
Now obviously we only want to show this if we got an error,
so we need to set show to something else and that something else needs to come from the wrapped component,
we need that information
if it did fail. To get that information, we should add a second argument to our higher order function
here,
the axios instance which was used so that we can set up an error handler, a global error handler on it.
Now to use that instance here, I will change this functional component into a class-based one because
I want to add the componentDidMount lifecycle hook to set up the axios interceptors.
Now theoretically of course, you could keep this as a functional component and use the useEffect hook
here to do the same,
that would be OK as well
and of course we'll see it in action in that module where I convert the entire project to use hooks.
So for now, I'll go with the lifecycle method approach and convert this to a class which should now extend
the component object from React,
so I need to import that,
class extends component. As you can see it's an anonymous class,
I don't set up a name here because I never use that class,
I return it here,
it's a class factory essentially, withErrorHandler creates these classes.
Now in there, we clearly need a render method where we in the end return what we returned in our functional
component here,
so simply return
that. Of course props is now this prop since we changed it to a class, we can get rid of that part down
there now
and now with this, we can add componentDidMount here and in componentDidMount,
we can now set up our axios listener,
so on the axios instance here, we can now set up our global interceptor which also allows us to handle
errors. So I'll add interceptors here, then response and then with use, add a function I want to use.
So this function here will get the response and then do something with it
but I'm not really interested in that first argument, so I'll pass null here.
The second argument is the one I'm interested in,
that's the error case where I get an error. Here
I then want to show my error modal, so for that I'll now add a state where I will simply set error to null
initially and in here, I will then set or call this set state and set error to the error I'm
getting here back from Firebase and this happens to be an object which also contains an error message,
on the message property
you can simply console log that error to see how this object looks like.
So now I'm setting that error here
once we got one, now what I'll also do is I'll add a new interceptor for a request, so there
I'll call use and I'm not really interested in the request but there's one thing I want to do in there,
I want to call this set state and clear any errors, so that whenever I send a request, I don't have my
error set up anymore, so that I definitely clear it here.
So now on the modal, I will only show it if this state error is not null essentially
and then in there, I can output this state error and then again, there will be a message property on the
error object returned by Firebase. Now there's one more thing we have to do,
the modal component we created also exposes the clicked property which occurs when we click the backdrop
and in this case of course I also want to clear the error because then we click the modal,
I don't want to show it anymore,
I have to get rid of the error. So I'll also add clicked here and there,
I will call a method I have to create in my withErrorHandler component, I'll name it
errorConfirmedHandler,
this simply is a method where I will call this set state and set error to null too and I will assign it
here, this errorConfirmedHandler.
Now with this setup here, there is one more thing I want to do,
this state error message which I'm outputting here will throw an error initially because the modal component
is always present even if we don't show it there.
So what I'll do is I'll simply add a ternary expression where I'll say this state error?
Only if this is null, then I'll output that otherwise I'll output null, so output nothing.
Now with that if I save this and go back to the application, we'll get cannot read property interceptors
which makes sense because we try to run this on axios but we don't receive axios, we expect to get it
as an argument
but in the burger builder where I use withErrorHandler, I'm only passing the burger builder component,
the wrapped component.
So here I simply have to pass axios which we are importing here and which is our axios instance.
Now with that, there's one more thing we have to do. In our interceptors
we of course have to return something, when sending the request, we have to return the request config
so that the request can continue and for the response, I also want to implement a response handler here
where I simply return the response, this is the shortest possible syntax for doing that.
Now with that if we save all of that and we go back to the application and we add a burger, this should
still work, it does,
we can still save a burger, now let's mess something up and let's see if it also works. In the burger
builder container where we sent the request,
if we now change that URL and maybe remove the .json which I said is a valid or an important
part of the API endpoint for the Firebase database we're sending the request to here.
So if we remove that, it should fail,
so now if we try to store a burger, we indeed get a network error message here.
Now closing by clicking on the backdrop doesn't work though, so let's quickly check why this is the case.
Let me quickly have a look,
I'm using the wrong prop. In the modal of course,
clicked is for the backdrop,
the prop the backdrop exposes, the modal then uses modal closed.
This is the method we try to execute here,
so this is the property we should implement,
so modal closed is the correct prop.
Now with that again if we try to send this with the wrong URL, we get the error but we can dismiss it.
So now we got global error handling in place and I'm going to fix that
orders URL again.
So now we're handling both the success case and the error case,
we're showing a loader
as long as needed
and with that, we get a robust application with a reusable higher order component which we can wrap around
any component which uses axios to handle its errors.