In the last lecture we made sure that can handle errors
and with that we get a robust application which allows us to post our orders to our back-end, that
already is a lot.
Now there's one more thing I want to do though, I also want to be able to get some data from the
back-end
and why don't we get our ingredients from there?
So the ingredients which we setup like this, why don't we get the ingredients dynamically from the
back-end?
For that, let's go to Firebase first and let's close the orders node.
Now let's add a new node by clicking on the plus directly next to your root
name here and let's name this ingredients,
then add this plus here on the right to add a nested element and there ingredients should really just
be our key-value pairs.
So there, we might have sell it with a value of zero,
click this add button then and now add more and let's add meat with a value of zero, let's add bacon with
a value of zero,
so I'm using the same ingredients as before because I only support these
but you could of course now add more to both your front-end code and your back-end
and let me also add cheese here and of course you could also set up different starting values.
So now we get that ingredients
node, here is the URL to it, you need to append .json to really access it though
and now the goal is to initialize our ingredients here with the ingredients we just stored on Firebase.
So still in the burger builder component, I want to set up the state dynamically and you learned that
a good place for fetching data is componentDidMount,
so this is the method I want to use.
So I'll add it here, componentDidMount like this and there I now want to reach out with axios. So I'm using
axios with a get request and reach out to that URL I just copied with .json at the end.
So this will now send a request to get our ingredients,
I'll then add a then block here to handle the response we get back and that response should of course
contain our ingredients object.
So now the goal is to set our state, here ingredients to that object,
so I'm actually going to set this to null initially here because we're now fetching it from the database
and there, I will now call this set state and set ingredients equal to response and there, there will
be a data object which actually contains the data we fetched.
Now if we save that and we go back to our application here, you see we get an error because now when
we try to loop through our ingredients at the start of the app, that of course fails because initially
ingredients is now null,
we're only fetching it at the start and that's a typical use case in applications,
you fetch data when it loads, so parts of the UI which depend on the data will therefore fail.
Now this of course can easily be prevented by checking if we have ingredients before rendering anything
which depends on ingredients, like the burger here.
Now there are a couple of ways where we can handle this,
I want to handle it here in my container,
I want to show a spinner instead of the burger and instead of the build controls whilst I am waiting
for the ingredients to load.
So to do that, I'll add another variable here which I'll name burger and this will be the burger and
the build control, so I'll
cut it from there and assign it to that variable
and now of course, this will fail due to us having adjacent elements here in JSX which is not liked
by default
as you learned
but you can either return an array or use our aux helper component here essentially.
So I'll wrap it with that,
keep in mind that's not rendering anything to the screen, so we're not destroying our layout but burger
should of course actually only be that if we have ingredients.
So I'll actually overwrite a variable burger which I'll set prior to that, burger, where I will use
the spinner and then I only want to overwrite it if this state ingredients is basically not null,
so that will only be the case if it was loaded.
So I'll move my code where I overwrite the burger variable inside of this if statement,
so now by default, the burger is just a spinner
and now I can output it here below the modal, I'll output burger with single curly braces.
However we'll also face another issue, the order summary will also use the ingredients and therefore fail.
So here, we should simply also add something and set order summary to null by default and then add
the same check or actually we already have that check of course, where we overwrite that order summary
variable with the order summary if ingredients are set, so let's add this after this burger code here maybe.
So now we are overwriting the order summary in that same if statement we created a second ago, of course
I also want to make sure that we overwrite this
again if loading was set, so after this if statement where we check for ingredients, I'll add this old if
statement where we check for the loading state to overwrite order summary when needed.
So now when we save this and go back to the application, you saw that spinner for the fraction of a second
and thereafter you can get going and you can create that burger which you can see is still handled correctly,
so this all works.
The cool thing now is if we go to Firebase and we update our ingredients, so that for example we always
start with meat,
we can simply set meat to one here and confirm with enter and then go back to our burger
and if we now reload it, you'll see we already start with one meat,
so that's pretty cool.
So now we're also fetching this from the back-end and now we really improved our application and we
have both a post and a get request.
Now the cool thing is we're showing the spinner but if we now are removing the JSON end here of our
URL where we're getting the ingredients, just as an example, if we're removing that and we go back,
we don't get the error mode.
Now that's not cool,
why are we not getting that? That can be hard to spot.
The reason actually can be found in our withErrorHandler function.
We're setting up our interceptors in the componentDidMount hook and it worked great for the post
request
but think about that lifecycle diagram,
there you see componentDidMount is actually called after all child components have been rendered, which
means after componentDidMount was completed in the child components.
Now think about our withErrorHandler, here we're wrapping this wrapped component which is our burger
builder container for example because there we are using withErrorHandler on the export,
so we're essentially wrapping the burger builder and that of course has one implication, componentDidMount
in the withErrorHandler will only be called once componentDidMount was called here
and since we reach out to the web in componentDidMount of the wrapped component, we never set up our interceptors.
The fix is simple, here
I'll use componentWillMount. However in the future, this React lifecycle hook or lifecycle method will
not be supported anymore
and therefore you can also just use the constructor because the general idea here is that we execute
this code when this component here gets created
and with that, I mean that component object
and of course the constructor also runs when this gets created,
so therefore using the constructor instead of componentWillMount will work in exactly the same way.
This will be called before the child components are rendered
and we're not causing side effects here,
we're just registering the interceptors and we want to do that before the child components are rendered.
Now with that if we save this and we reload the application, we get that error modal but then we get another
error that we fail to set our state.
The reason for this is that the
then block gets executed in our burger builder even though we have an error.
Now the reason for that simply is that we're not having a catch method here in componentDidMount of
the burger builder.
If we catch an error there and simply don't do anything with it for example, then we will already not
get this anymore because now we're not calling the then block anymore. We can still dismiss the network
error and our application is now broken,
so we probably would want to handle that specific error case here for this specific page by for example
also setting the UI here.
So there, we could also set some error state,
so now in the burger builder which is null initially or false maybe
and then inside here if we get an error, if we catch this, then we call set state and set error to true.
Now with that we can go down to the render method and we want to output an error message for this case
where our application becomes unusable.
Here we set burger to spinner,
now we actually don't want to show the spinner but our the application is not usable at all
error message if we have the error equal to true.
So here we could check if this state error,
if that is true, then we actually want to show a paragraph where we say ingredients can't be loaded,
this is our worst case scenario
otherwise we're showing the spinner or we're overwriting it with the ingredients if we got them.
So now if we save this, we get the spinner and then we see ingredients can't be loaded,
now our application is broken but at least we show it to the user,
of course once we fix that link by adding .json at the end again,
now of course the ingredients will load as you can see here, we see the spinner for a fraction of a second, the
ingredients are there and we can continue using our application just fine.
So this is now all working,
now we got a really robust application where we are both storing orders and we're fetching content.
Now of course, we could also implement code to fetch the orders from our database, from our back-end here,
so that is something we want to work on next, routing, being able to switch pages even though technically,
we only have one page in that single page application.