Now in this module, we obviously added a lot of logic to our burger builder again.
There is one improvement or fix we should apply to it though, can be subtle to spot but it really improves
our application,
Let's have a look at this withErrorHandler higher order component.
There we obviously added Our interceptors in componentWillMount
and of course it makes sense to add them there because we wanted to make sure that we can intercept
errors and hence show this error modal we set up in this higher order component,
we have one issue though. This withErrorHandler method can be wrapped around multiple components,
that's the whole idea of having this higher order component
otherwise we could have put that code directly into the burger builder if that were the only component
where we want to use that.
Right now, it is the only component, we're using it
but again our higher order component is of course not limited to the burger builder.
The problem we have is if we add this higher order component, withErrorHandler to other components,
we'll call componentWillMount again and again of course because the class component we return it is
higher order component is created every time this is wrapped around an existing component,
so every time we call withErrorHandler on the element we're exporting as we do in the burger builder.
So we're actually attaching multiple interceptors in our application and we're attaching them to the
same axios instance.
The problem of course is and we don't have that
right now and we will face later in the course, the mentioned routing will lead to the problem,
once we have more pages where we might use withErrorHandler, we of course create this instance here
multiple times, this component here and therefore all the old interceptors, so all the interceptors we
set up when we wrapped this around another component which might not be needed anymore still exist.
So we have a lot of that interceptor sitting in memory which actually are not that but which still
react to our requests and in the worst case, they lead to errors or do somehow change the state of
our application
but even in the best case, they leak memory because that's code that still runs that is not required
anymore.
So we should actually remove the interceptors when this component gets unmounted,
so when this specific instance of our withErrorHandler wrapper is not needed anymore and there actually
is a lifecycle hook for this too, it's componentWillUnmount.
Now as the name suggests, this is a lifecycle method which is executed at the point of time a component
isn't required anymore.
Alternatively if you're using a functional component here and you're not returning this class-based
component,
so if you're effectively using the useEffect hook thus far, then you would write this code in the return
function of useEffect since this function runs whenever the cleanup is done for this component.
Now to be able to remove an interceptor here, we need to store a reference to the interceptors we create
in properties of this class.
Now we have the state property already,
we can simply add new properties.
So for that, I will simply create a new property on the fly by using this,
the this keyword to refer to the class and then any name of your choice,
I'll name this the request interceptor, maybe like this,
request interceptor and we'll store the result of our interceptor setup which is just a reference to the
interceptor passed back by axios automatically and I'll do the same for the response interceptor here.
So now I have two new properties in my class and I can now use these properties in will unmount to remove
the interceptors. There
we can now simply use axios interceptors, just like we created them but now we can also access request
and response there and call eject and eject
now requires the reference to the interceptor.
So here, this request interceptor and I'll simply duplicate this to also do the same for the response,
so for the response object, I'll call eject and then call response interceptor.
And now with that, we got this set up in componentWillUnmount and we should remove our interceptors
with that preventing memory leaks.
Now to quickly see if that works, I'll save that file and then I'll go into the app.js file which
is where we add the burger builder and I want to add some code to remove it after some time just to see
if will unmount gets called.
So there, I will simply console log will unmount and I want to output this request interceptor and
this response interceptor, the two properties we added to see if they are set at the beginning of will unmount
because I'm using them thereafter.
So now with that saved, let's go back to app.js and to make sure that burger builder disappears after
a while, I'll temporarily add a state to my app component, it is a class-based component so I can of course
do this and I will simply add a show property which is true initially and I will then use it here with
this state show to show the burger builder or show null which essentially removes the burger builder
of course because it's only added to the DOM if show is true.
So now I just need a way to unset show after a while and for that
and again this is all just for testing, I'll add componentDidMount here and there I will simply use
the normal set timeout method provided by Javascript
and after 5 seconds, I want to execute this function here and in that function, I'll call set state and
set show to false
and again I will remove this code in a second,
it's only there to test if this works, if it does call will unmount.
So with that, that let's save this and now let's reload the application, we see the burger and let's wait
five seconds and we should then see will unmount
and we see zero zero
and that's actually correct because these are simply the IDs.
There are IDs being kept the memory by axios for both the request and response interceptors, so two
different lists of interceptors and they start with index zero.
We added one to each list,
one request and one response interceptor,
so that is why we see two zeros here.
So what we can see is it does work,
we can now remove that console log statement from unmount, it does successfully get this reference
to the interceptor and we can rely on eject working and this will just ensure that whenever we don't
need the burger builder component anymore
and of course this is not the case right now in the application but will soon be, that we clean up the
interceptors which we attached due to using withErrorHandler on the burger builder so that if we reuse
withErrorHandler in our application, we don't create more and more interceptors with the old ones living
on.
So with that, I can remove my code here in the app.js file to have a normally working application again,
so I'll remove all the code we added, the state and componentDidMount with the set timeout, so that we have
the same app component as before
but now again with the improved application where we actually remove interceptors we don't need anymore.