So stalled components are a pretty nice way of mixing javascript and CSX and getting components elements
H HTML elements with certain possibly dynamic styles added to them.
Now a lot of people like stalled components and you can probably already tell why now.
I also like styled components but I'm personally also a fan of having CSA as Stead is scoped to a certain
file or scope to a certain component and still lives inside of CSA as files.
Though I am personally not the biggest fan of this CSR s and JavaScript mixture since it loads the JavaScript
files a little bit.
We have all that extra code in there and since a lot of high to ease or environments you only get poor
IDE support when writing code here.
The auto completion and so on for a c as s commands and CSA as values is much better in C is as follows
typically so you can't absolutely use that but I personally am not the biggest fan of it and so I want
to show you yet another way of scoping styles to your components.
So of writing styles which only apply to a specific component instead of the entire application because
that is an important thing.
Often you really want to make sure that your styles don't apply everywhere to everywhere in your application
but only to certain parts.
For example if we would grab this code here and temporarily nowhere did we want to change it dynamically
sometimes if we grab this code here and add it to app CSA s then we could pass this year into a button
class lets say so let's move this in here and then here we have anything with a button clause and a
hover state which gets this style and then here of course we don't have this dynamic code but we just
have green here and we just have light green down there and this would be valid code but now everything
with a button class will get these styles which means if I add the button clause here to this button
down there and for that I will revert it to a regular button not using the style component removed all
the attribute and just add a class name here of button.
Then of course this button would get that style but any other button anywhere else in the app with the
same class name would get the same style too.
So if we have a button in person J as we don't but if we had one here which also has this button C as
this class it would get the same style and off.
That's not what you want you want to make sure instead that your styles or scope to a certain component
and that can be achieved with a novel concept as well.
CSX modules for that I will remove the stalled button here because I don't need it anymore.
Remove the stalled component and now for CSX modules to work.
We need to tweak the configuration of our project a little bit.
The underlying build configuration so the configuration which takes our code transforms it and bundles
it together to be precise.
We need to tweak the configuration if we're using react scripts.
Shown one here.
I recommend this version because with that you actually get a starting setup where you have a class
based component here which makes it easier to follow along in this course where we first start with
class based components and later focus on functional components with hooks in greater detail.
So that's why I'm using version 1 here.
If you are using react scripts words 2 or higher you have an alternative approach of enabling this feature
I'm about to show you here however I am using version 1 so we'll show you the approach that works with
this version.
For that you need to quit your development server and then run NPM run eject in your project folder.
Running this script.
What this will do is it will eject from this under the hood configuration where you don't really have
access to the underlying web packed conflict file and so on and give you access to the conflict files
so that you can tweak how your code is bundled together and so on and there is something we will need
to tweak there.
So if you run NPM run eject here your ask if you want to inject each act and you can answer why you're
free yes and you might get an error.
As I'm getting here that you have uncommitted changes.
For that I'll just add and you commit.
This only applies if you are using get for version control if you're not using that you will not get
that error.
So I'll quickly create a committee and then rerun and Pam Brown eject and Sir Y for yes here and now
what you get is a new scripts and then you can think folder and in that conflict folder here you'll
find a webpage conflict but DAF chars file and a webpage conflict out prod J.S. file.
These are already configuration files which are used under the hood by this react tooling here.
You'll see the package of Jason File now all the changed.
We have way more packages here now.
These are Indian packages used under the hood by create react app to give you that development server
and build your app and bundle it together.
And if you as this disk consecration for web spec which is the tool which is used for all of that now
then there are a lot of things you can tweak and you should only tweak them if you really know what
you're doing.
There is one specific option that's important to us though.
If you scroll down until you find this test CSA s thing here you will see that we're using CSR as loader
and there you'll find some options.
And now this is the part which you can tweak and which you should tweak if your config file looks a
bit differently.
Also check out the text lecture after this lecture where I show differently looking conflict files and
how you would adjust those.
So have a look at this lecture in that case if it looks like this then here's what you need to tweak
in the options here.
You have import loaders 1 one now there you'll all need to add a modules entry and set this to true
and then a local indent name entry which you set to a string which should look like this.
Square brackets name underscore underscore square brackets local between the brackets underscore underscore
brackets hash colon base 64 5.
Now that's looking very strange.
What does this all mean.
This enables to see us as modules feature which we're about to use and this will be used by that feature
to dynamically generate unique CSA as class names in the end.
Now we all need to do the same in the profile so you can copy these two lines go to the webpage conflict
profile and also search for the S test there and they are all to add these two entries to these options
off the CSA as loader.
Now with that you can rerun NPM start and it should now still work just fine without any issues.
Now what do we get by adding D configuration items though if we go to app J S we can now import from
that C as s file in a different way.
We can import colossus from for example and you can name this year whoever you want.
Now this is a different way of importing from the CSA as file which is now supported by the underlying
bill script because of our tweaks we just made.
What this will do is it will import all the classes we export here for example button which I'll label
with the upper case B don't need to do that.
Just want to do it to be in line with app.
It will import these classes here.
In the end ask properties on this object.
What does this mean.
It means that if we go down to our button I don't add button like this.
Instead here we add something dynamically.
We point at classes start button.
Now we need to be careful here because I already got a class's constant here.
So to avoid name clashes I'll renamed as two assigned classes here and here and here and what I push
here is all not red but instead classes dodge red referring to that import we're importing from the
CSX file and here it's class stock bold
now we all need to tweak this here and point at classes dot app so effectively I am pointing at properties
on these on this class classes object and the properties I'm pointing at are class names.
I set up an app C.S. s App rad bold button.
Now what am I doing here to see us as modules feature is a feature applied by some tool which is part
of the build process.
So if the process which takes our code and then compiles it transforms it and bundles it together and
this process simply detects this kind of import from a CSX file and understands that we don't just want
to add the CSX as it is but instead it now looks into the CSX file transforms every class name here
to a unique one to a random unique one and returns us a map of these generated unique class names mapped
to D class names we chose here as properties and is object which we import so every class name we have
to see as his file is now a property of this imported object and the value for every property will be
this randomly generated unique class name generated by this package.
The result is that if I now save this you'll see everything still works but if we analyze this spot
and you see the closet has is now actually app button some random hash this is what I mean.
This is this randomly generated name following our naming convention we set up in the webpage config
in the end.
This is guaranteed to be unique only in this component only new web component so we can't clash with
other components because only here I'm importing from app assassin in that way if I use let's say Button
class name written like this in another part of my app it will not clash with the styles here because
this will actually not be applied as a button class to the element.
But as this generated name this is the idea behind CFS modules and therefore they allow us to move code
in to see us as follows and still imported in a way that is scoped to this component.
Now the question of course is how can we now implement such dynamic style changes.
Now we're not setting the styles in the javascript code anymore but in C Ss files.
Well we just have to add different as classes based on the styles we want.
So we can't go to app CSX and then there we can add a new class ret.
And here I specify a selector that this only has an effect if it is on an element which all danced a
Button class and in there in button red we can now set background color to red and I also add button
Don to red hover to set specific hover stalls where I want to use background color and set this to Selman.
Now the default button hover sub will still apply but this will override the background color.
The color here will be capped.
So now with that we added a new class.
And by the way this is not to be confused with this red clause.
This has a lower case r this has an opera case R and this also has only the fact if it's on a button.
So now an app yes we can change our classes here on the button dynamically based on the condition we
have for that.
So we could say we have let's say not that style icons here but up there below or persons maybe we have
a button class variable which initially is an array where we just have classes dot button with an opera
case B.
And remember this will simply be a pointer at this unique class name which is generated by the C assess
modules package and it's this button class which I'll one up lie down there.
So here I'll add Button class join like this.
So because we have an array here I want to join all the classes that are in there together with a white
space in between we can of course also named as Button classes if you prefer it that well.
And now here in this place where we need to change styles dynamically we set Button class or we don't
set it but we push a new class onto it and that's classes start red upper case are using this special
red class we just added.
So now this will be an array Button class will be an array with the Button class and with the red class
and both combined here will have this effect.
So now with that if we save this and we reload you will see that if I toggle as we get the red button
with the Selman background we don't toggle we have the green button with the green background and you'll
see on the right that a new class gets additive when we toggle.
So this is how we could implement this with C as this modules we simply add differences as classes and
now our way of implementing this would be to say well instead of my app class every button should have
to stall.
So here we could say app button like this using the button tag selector here.
Not a class.
This is just a tax collector now just app as a class selector.
And then here we say well any button with the red clause inside of our app class we'll have these spells.
So now we use a more complex or a little bit more complex CSF selector.
We say every button is out of element which has the app clause should have that style and every button
inside of our element with the app class which also has to read class should have these styles.
Now since my button here is inside of an element with the app class this button will get these styles
and then we could simplified this here to say we just want to add button class here and button classes
not an array but button clauses equal to classes stored right here.
So to my special class which I want to add eventually and by default button class simply is empty.
So by default we go to the place where button classes to find here because we're not working with a
default button class but any button inside of an app class decorate that element We'll have that style
and we would have the same effect as before.