Now let's also apply.
See ISS modules to person J.S. so there instead of hostile they've all used a regular div here just
like this.
Basically what we had before but now I will import from the C as file again again using this syntax
beer to import classes from that file.
Now we can get rid of that style.
If we don't need it anymore.
We don't need that import anymore.
And now here I just want to add class name classes stopped and now it's up to you what you want to use
there.
And here I'll assign a dot Person class and that means said now in Person C S S we need to ensure that
we have such a person class which we do.
And then again this will be transformed to a unique random or pseudo random class name and b mapped
to disperse some property on this imported object so that we can access t generated class name here
and assign it to the death.
And of course here we can then all ze was immediate query just like this.
This will work because in here.
And that's really important with CSX modules.
You write regular CSX code you have normal CSX files.
Just the way you add them is special and they are for now here we toggled is.
We have our same person style we had before where the boxes don't get wider than four hundred and fifty
pixels and Oberweis take up 60 percent of the width.
So this is CSX modules and ultimately it's of course up to you what you prefer.
I'm just a fan of having my javascript code and the as this code separated and we've CSX modules that's
very simple whilst at the same time having the power of scoping CSX to certain components so did what
we defined here on this person clause does not apply to every person class in the entire app but only
two person clauses used in the files where we import from the person see as file like this.
And this is a syntax which I therefore like a lot if you prefer one of the obvious in Texas.
You can of course use data as well you can use styled components or radium throughout this course.
However I will use see us as modules just as shown here because of these splitting of CSX and JavaScript
which in my opinion also makes it easier to focus on javascript no one last word about an alternative
way of using C as as modules if you're using react scripts to dot X or higher.
When I mentioned that you eject I mentioned dead you only need to do this on Version 1 if you're using
Q Dot X or higher.
You can use the syntax automatically.
The only addition you need to do is you need to import from DOT modules CSX and rename your CSX fall
to dock module dot CSX and then this will automatically work without ejecting here.
I'll not do it because we already did eject and it's fine like this but if you are using a later version
of React scripts you can save the eject step and just import from a dot module CSX file and see us as
modules will be unlocked.