So we had a look at radium which is one package that helps us with styling React Components.
Another very popular package and third party library you can use for dad is styled components to styled
components library.
Now what are styled components or what does this library about.
This library is all about.
Guess what.
Styling components and making that very simple on style dash components dot com.
You can learn all about it here if you click on documentation.
But of course I want to introduce you to this library and show you the core basics of it.
In this course now to get started with that library with first of all have to install it.
And for that we can run this command here.
So simply copy this
and then quit your development server and simply run npm install dash dash save style dash components
in your react project and this will now install this package as a dependency.
In the meantime I will already get rid of my radium import here and all of the radium wrapper down there.
They are for all temporarily keep this around so that they can copy and paste to stall later but will
not set it up like this soon in AB jars.
I'll also get rid of radium of this import here and in their deal for all also get rid of the radium
wrapper we have at the bottom.
So let's make sure we get rid of all our radium traces here so that we're not using radium anywhere
because we're now going to switch and we're going to basically use C as as styling or CSX in JavaScript
styling with the help of this package.
So with it installed how does this package work.
How can we use styled components.
Of course the official docs or you official page has got you covered regarding that as well.
And what you see there is that in the annual import one thing from that stalled components package and
then you have this strange syntax down there and now it is is something you might have never seen before.
There is back tick back tick thing here after some of our code.
This is regular javascript though it's a feature called tacked templates and attached you find a link
where you can learn more about it.
It has nothing to do with react that is a way lable in vanilla javascript as well.
And in the end what this here is is a function call so button here would be a function or a method on
the stalled object to be precise and instead of having parentheses with function arguments as you're
used to you instead have to back takes between which you can pass text and then this text is the and
passed into the spot method in a special way which we don't have to care about where you can learn more
about than this attached link.
We just have to note that it will be passed into this but method here in such a way that this method
uses whatever you pass this text here as styling for this well button which this method creates back
takes in general can be used in javascript to create a so-called template literal.
So even without dad combination of a method with back takes you can't create strings in javascript with
just back takes and attached you all to find a link which introduces you to template liberals in case
you're not aware of them it's a regular jobs good feature has nothing to do with react but this becomes
cleaner if we use it.
So let's go back to our project and we want to style the dev here in the example of person J s right.
So in order to do that let's first of all import styled from styled dash components.
And then here instead of using the div like this year let's comment this out and let's instead return
styled dot death.
This styled object which we're importing from styled components basically has a method for every H2
male element.
You could create.
So you have div here you have the button here you have an anchor tag you have paragraph you have a h1
tag end zones have all these H Tim l elements a way double here as methods.
And here we want to render a death.
So we use death now as you see in the official docs then we use this strange syntax div in the end as
a function but we don't call it as such.
Instead we use this tact template approach and add to back takes after it.
So did we have style div like this.
Now the obvious question is what goes between these two back ticks here though between these back takes
go your styles.
So here we can actually go to the person C as as file comment this temporarily back in and then copy
this entire style and then commented all out if we want to actually remove or comment out the person
C assess the import here and now between these two back ticks we add our style however without the person
selector instead just the style properties like this so that we simply say this div should have these
styles now we can all add a media query here again without this selector though just with the property
we want to apply and the styled components package behind the scenes we'll make sure that these styles
including the media query end up on this def which is created here now at the moment we have invalid
code though we have some other code down there which should go between our two div tax the div opening
and closing tag.
So actually the solution here is or one solution is to grab this cactus and create a new component here.
So here we can create a new component style div maybe and there we create are styled death with this
template tag syntax copy in all that CSX code here without selectors.
As mentioned
and we'll be good to go.
Now important here.
I'm starting with the upper case character because I plan on using this component right in this file
down here.
I now use stall div as a regular react component because that's really important.
Every method provided by this styled object no matter if that's div age 1 or whatever it is returns
a react component.
So here we're not creating a react component where we get props and returns J is x.
No because this already returns our ReACT component so this already is a functional or class based.
We don't know component.
So instead of creating a function here a functional component we just stored the result of this method
call in our style.
They've constant here because this already is a valid react component provided by that third party library
and with Dad we can restart our development server here so that we can see this in action.
Make sure you're using a recent version of React for this.
In my case I'm using react 16 dots 10
and then you should be able to click on toggle persons and actually see what you saw before and just
to prove that this works if I remove the media query you see now I have these bigger boxes here on bigger
screens always 60 percent of my screen with if I re added and save and toggle you see now this width
gets applied.
So now the style components Library is doing its job and is styling these components and therefore again
we have a nice mixture of CSX and JavaScript all in one file with help of these stalled components.