No style components are nice but how do they actually work.
Which magic trick are they doing.
Well for that let's inspect this in the developer tools.
What we see there if we expect these rendered deaths is that they have CSF classes attached to them.
Classes with very strange names which we certainly didn't define these class names are automatically
added by the styled components library because keep in mind that these deaths here are actually the
output of this death method.
Right.
We're not rendering a death.
We're rendering a style they have here which is the result of calling the dev method here and the end
with this tact template notation.
So this diff method returns a react component which the end renders a regular death a regular div with
such a C as as class.
And where's the content of this class coming from.
Well we can see that in the head of this document there we will see a style tag or multiple style tax
actually.
And if we have a look at these style text this style take here specifically with these attributes here
we see there's this strange class name again.
A day later we find the styles we set up here.
So the styles we set up here are not added as inline styles but instead the style components package
takes them puts them in to see us as class selectors and adds them to the head of document and then
just adds the appropriate CSO as class to the div which is returned by this component or which is created
as part of this component.
This is how style components work under the hood which is great because that means you're not working
with inline styles which can have certain disadvantages.
For example you're not really taking advantage of the cascading nature of C.S. s with them.
No.
Instead you have regular C as his classes automatically managed for you by style components which makes
this a really great solution.
Let's also applied to app GST offer in app J.S..
We also have some styles here which we previously added with radium just as we did it in person.
J.S. There by the way we can also get rid of that style constant here we don't need it anymore.
We've styled components but an app has it's the same.
We got this style constitution.
We don't need it anymore like this because we're not using radium anymore.
Now this style constant here is important for our button.
So in the end what we want to create is a stalled button right.
Now again we can do this with the stalled components package and side note of course you can all the
story your style components in separate files and then reuse them across multiple files if you need
to hear I just happen to only need that Dave and this person component and that button in the app component
but you could absolutely share them across files.
So here I am importing style from styled components again and with that I want to create my style.
Button so here I'll have my style button.
Of course you can name this constant however you want and there.
I created with styled button like this again using this tact template syntax here.
Now here we have our style which we can copy in that style constant and added here in our template literal.
Now we don't need the quotes here because we're writing regular C.S. s here.
That's important.
You write regular C.S. s here.
So you'd also need to use regular CSA as properties.
You're not using camel case here anymore because of what you write in your will end up in the head of
your document between style tax as you saw before.
So we write regular C as s here we don't need to adhere to any special javascript syntax here because
it's just C.S. s so let's add semicolons at the end of every line remove all quotes and get rid of all
camel case notations.
Now the cool thing about style components is you can just add a hover a pseudo selector like this with
a little tweak.
You need to add Ampersand symbol in front of it and this will tell the style components package that
this belongs to this button which is spread out and that there it should apply it hover style.
Or be aware of this hover style that here we have the background color light green like that and the
color black like this.
So this is how we would translate this to regular CSA as applied to this button which is created by
this.
Button method in the end and now we can use that stop button.
So let's go down here and let's replace our button here with styled button.
Now important we don't apply to inline style like this anymore.
We can still add on click though because this button component which is created by the style components
package has all the normal props every button has.
So on click ends on are still available there.
If we now save that and we reload we still see the button here and you see the hovering fact when I
will hover over it and just to again prove that this is coming from the style components.
If I were to temporarily remove that hover code here you see now I have no hover effect here.
So that's really style components doing their work.
Let's reactive though.