Now you might also remember that we had a little addition here on this spot and we just worked on when
we were showing persons then actually the background color of the buttons should change to read and
hear the hover stall should make sure that we styled a button differently if we hover over it basically.
Now how can we change styles conditionally like this when using styled components.
Thankfully it's super super simple.
We have a style button here right.
And we want to change some styles based on some circumstance outside of the component.
So in this case based on show person's well we're dead we can't just pass a prop to stall button any
prop of our choice for example all but the name is really up to you and then pass the value in this
case this state show persons.
So basically the state which is important for us to change the styling and that is to show person style
because previously we changed styles and if block now I'm just for wording is important state on this
all Prop 2 style button.
Now the only question is how can we use this all prop inside of our styled button component to change
the background color or to hover stalls.
And for that we can use a neat feature this year with the back takes is a template literal it's regular
javascript which in the end creates a string.
Now that is a string where we can dynamically inject content though with a special syntax.
And again this is just JavaScript has nothing to do with react.
You can at a dollar sign and then two curly braces here this allows you to dynamically insert something
into this long string which is created here.
And here we actually can get a function where we receive props and then we have to return a value we
want to render in this place and there we can check if props all which is that prop I add it down there
if you remember here all if Dad is in the end true in our case here or not
so here we can check of props out with a ternary expression is Data's true then.
Here we want to have a red background.
Otherwise we want to have that greenback run from before some returning a string here.
Now this dynamic expression here is also passed into the spot method and yet automatically by javascript.
And this also is a sudden tax or a usage of this template literal which the styled components package
understands if we inject such a function into dad style string here the styled components package will
have a look at it and will pass in the props that we pass to the button to that function so we can expect
that as argument to that function here and then we can use the props here and returned a text which
should be output here and which should be used in the style and yen.
And so therefore now if we save this and this reload you see this still is green but if you click on
it it has a red background and this is all done because in the head section if we inspect our styles
again you see here we got conditional styles we better get back on color green and we also got the background
color red here with a different see says class it's a bit hard to read because it's optimized and compressed
here but here you see background color red.
And up there you see background color green and these are different CSF has classes in the end which
are used to add these colors and the style components package will simply swap these classes here if
you inspect the but then watched a class on the right will swap these classes based on our condition.
So that's all the magic quote unquote done by that package.
And of course we can use the syntax here not just in this place but also use it here to have Selman
as a background color or light green or all the down there a color which I used before of black.
So that doesn't change.
So we don't need to change it here we don't need to add this special syntax here.
So with that if we now reload if I click it we have a red button with a Salmond background if I hover
over it or we're not viewing persons have a green button with a light green button.
These are styled components and styled components is a package which gives us a very popular way of
combining CSX and JavaScript where we write normal CSX but we mix it with this javascript syntax and
installed components package then does all the magic of extracting this putting it into a C as is class
and adding this class dynamically to this button which does spot method in this case creates and then
we can use this here as a regular react component which just happens to have some styles attached to
it.
Therefore style components are definitely also a package I can recommend that you have a look at if
you're looking into styling your components.