Now you learned how to read and understand arrow messages and how to find logical errors.
Sometimes you want to know the current state of your react app and wealth.
You might be able to figure that out with the developer tools.
It can be inconvenient.
Thankfully there is a cool extension you can add to Chrome D react.
Developer Tools let's install it together.
You can simply google for react developer tools and you will will find the github repository where you
can learn more about them how to use them and can even contribute to the project or you had right to
the Chrome Web Store.
No no worries these are free in the Chrome Web Store.
I already added them to Chrome but you can click Add to grow if you haven't done so.
Once you added them you probably need to restart chrome and thereafter in the Chrome developer tools.
You should find queue entries here components and profiler with this react symbol next to them.
And if you click on components you should see something like this year you'll see a representation of
the react components currently rendered on the screen.
So at the moment this is my app component at the bottom you'll see props.
This component receives end state.
This component manages.
Now if I click toggle persons be there for all to see all the person components here.
We can all click on those to see the properties components get which components renders them and so
on.
You can also log such a component to the console so that you can dive into it in more detail here.
You can also inspect the matching DOM element which takes you to the elements tab and then show us your
which element is rendered by this concrete component and of course you can also inspect the source code.
You were taken to the source as Taproot can see that blaze breakpoints and so on.
You can also go to the settings here and tweak this a little bit there you can for example change how
things are displayed in a compact or a comfortable way.
If you have a light or dark mode here you can go to components specifically and also highlight certain
components of a certain type.
If you wish to but generally the default settings should be fine.
You can all use to select will here select something in the DOM and it automatically selects the react
component which is responsible for rendering that thing so the react afterwards are a great way of diving
deeper into this but you cannot just inspect things here.
Girls would change things.
For example they could change to age prop here and hence here we see 30.
We can of course also change the state and set this to false and it has the same effect as if we clicked
the toggle button.
So it's a great place to play around with your components test different states and props with ease
without having to hard code anything in your code and it's all great for inspecting what you have on
the screen and understanding what's getting displayed there and why and how things work together.