Now we had a look at lazy loading in this component and lazy loading like this still works and is perfectly
fine if you are using re-act 60 not six and you can check doesn't the package adjacent file and I have
a new demo project here by the way which you find attached to this lecture which you should download
extract NPM install and then NPM start.
So if you are using the latest re-act word in here or re-act 16 or 6 or higher then you have a new way
of lazy loading your routes because re-act 60 node 6 adds a new method on the re-act object.
The lazy method which you can use to load your data your components asynchronously.
Which means only when they are needed.
And let's have a look at how this works now.
So re-act lazy is a method that was added with re-act 60 not six.
That allows us to load components asynchronously which means they are only loading the code behind them
is only loaded when they are really required when they are being rendered.
And this is for example useful when having routing in your application because only when a user visits
a certain route that component will be required and re-act lazy allows you to defer the rendering and
the loading of the code of that component until it is required.
And that of course means that you don't load redundant code in advance.
It's not just useful for routing.
By the way whenever you have a use case whereas some component is loaded at a later point of time for
example because you have a check and some condition needs to be met to render a certain component in
all such cases you could use re-act lazy.
But let me show you how it works.
So let's go to the last Fall and here I'm using re-act router Dom to set up my browser router I'm using
Riak fragment here which is a feature that was added with re-act 16.00 2.
It's basically the same as our alks component we traded manually.
It's basically a component that you can use to well wrap over all components because you always need
that wrapping component and react.
It does not render a real Dom element and therefore does not distort your dom.
And instead of that fragment I have a little dummy navigation and then I have three routes here and
if you have a look at that we are on the welcome page by default and we can switch to the user and the
Post's page.
OK so that is this application.
Nothing fancy thus far.
Now we could use re-act lazy to only load the user into posts component when we need them.
Right now everything is loaded in advance but we might never visit these routes.
So loading the code behind them in advance is not ideal.
If there were an even bigger app with more code behind these components the issue would of course be
worse.
So we want to load these two components only when we need them and we can do that with this new method.
How is this method used.
Well let's start with the Post's component instead of importing it like this which will always force
today that will be loaded in advance.
We need to use dynamic import just as we did with that async component we created earlier and this module
we need to use dynamic import.
So we create a constant for that which we named posts.
You could name it whatever you want.
I just name it posts so that I can continue to not use that name down there.
And the value of that constant year will be a call to react dot lazy.
This new method that was added with re-act 606.
Now let's move these imports to the top.
Do not get any Lanting warnings.
And now instead of re-act lazy we'd pass a function.
Here I'll use an arrow function which returns an import statement and this is a dynamic import.
Which means it's basically executed when this code runs and react will executed when we try to render
this component.
And here we are again still point to a file which contains our post component and important for that.
We should use default exports named exports are not supported.
So now I'm importing my post component but only when this function runs which means only when re-act
thinks that we need to use it and react to things that we need to use it when it detects that it needs
to rendered it.
Now with that changed let's go down to that route here and there we now need to make a little change.
Instead of using that component let's use the render method here.
There we would receive all these Raut props.
But in the end here I want to return something I want to return a computer component that should be
rendered and there I now need to import a new component from re-act suspence component with an import.
That is what I want to render here.
Suspence like this.
And in-between all render posts.
So my constant as a component here and now let's add one more thing to that suspence component.
And that's the fallback proc which should be J as X code and they all add div where I say loading and
this will actually be displayed.
In cases where re-act basically postpones the rendering of this wrap component and shows as well fallback
in the meantime.
And of course that doesn't have to be a div with loading that could be a spinner or anything like that.
And now with all that let's save it go back to the front page look at the user's page load the Post's
page all working.
So what's special.
Well we can see what's special when we reload the page and then go to the Network tab.
Now after reloading clear it and now click on the post page and you will see that there it loaded a
new file and that is the file holding the code for this component and that is async rendering at async
loading in action because this component and its code is only fetched and rendered when we really need
it and therefore we avoid loading everything in advance which can of course drastically improve the
performance of your application depending on its size.
So this is a neat alternative to the other way of lazy loading pages which we had before.
A great advantage of this approach is that we of course can not just used is in a routing scenario.
We could of course also have a scenario where we don't use that browser router so let me comment all
that out.
And instead let's say I have a simple button here where I say toggle mode or anything like that we add
a new method to this component here.
Mode handler
and we add a state where we say show and it's false.
Initially let's say and then there I call this set state in the function a form of said States that
we can access the old state we return the updated state or our update to just state and I'll show you
the opposite of what it previously was.
So did I toggle that show mode.
And of course you can also add name to it differently.
Now we have that button.
Now I bind on Click here to my.
This mode handler.
And now I just want to render either the user or to post page.
Depending on that mode of course can also name that show posts for example up the détour too.
And now let's add a simple check where you check if this state show posts.
If that is true then I want to render my posts and data will also grab this code which suspends of course.
Let's copy that and move it up there.
Common that back in put dead in brackets.
So one to render with suspense suspends my posts show posts is true.
Otherwise I'll render my user component like this.
Now since I have two adjacent components here I'll again use re-act fragment or use you alks component
of course and wrap this.
And now if this change if I go back and I click on toggle mode we see that chunk was loaded and we see
the post page.
So here we all take advantage of this.
A sync rendering and that is really something useful and a great addition with re-act 6:16 we'll see
more on that async rendering thing in future versions.
And right now this is what we can use re-act lazy.
Please be aware that this will not work if you're trying to serve a side rendered.
Then this is not support that this API will not work yet.
But if you have a client side rendered application as we have it here and of course then this is a great
addition and definitely something you want to check out for cases where you conditionally render some
component needed in the if statement or be dead in a routing scenario.
Now of course one thing to keep in mind the benefit you will get out of this will be greater if you
have larger chunks of data behind your components.
If you have very simple components using suspends might actually be overkill and could even slow down
your application or be suboptimal.
At this point of time so lazy loading the code of course shows its full strength.
If we're talking about bigger chunks of code.