So let's start solving this assignment.
Let's start simple by creating an input field with a change listener and outputting the text below the
input field.
I'll do it and actually as soon as in the previous example I'll leave the assignment introductions here
all add a horizontal line self-closing element as all Jael's X elements have to be in.
James X if you don't put anything in between.
And there are now at an input element of type text just like that.
All those self-closing.
Now this alone doesn't do much.
We of course needer on change handler and execute some method there.
So let's add a method to our app component name that input changed handler and again use my syntax here
where I assign an arrow function to this property.
There I will get this event object passed into it automatically and then I'll want to store this in
state.
So I set up state as a property and there I'll simply add a state named user input.
The name is totally up to you.
It'll be an empty string initially.
And here in the input changed handler I want to update it.
We have set state all said user input equal to the end target values so to whatever the user entered.
And I will now also set up two way binding with that not only registered this as a handler here input
changed handler but also sets a value equal to this state user input to always reflect the latest value
in the input and I'll split it over multiple lines to make it easier to read.
Thus far nothing special.
Let's quickly check if it works Let's also hope the conc a lot to see if you've got any errors.
And let me ENTRAR something here.
This works we're not done yet though we should all the outputs the text below the input.
So I'll add a paragraph below my input element here and there.
I'll put some dynamic content this state user input clearly.
Let me save this too.
And now let's try this again.
Does looks pretty good.
I can see whatever I enter here below the input.
Then next step now is to create a new component which receives the text length not the text just the
length as a prop.
And here is a just a name validation component.
So I will do this I'll create a new folder for it.
Validation component and add develop Dacian component or javascript fall in there.
Now I mentioned in the problem video dead you won't need state in here so there there's no need to use
class and extend component.
We can instead use a function again name validation here and I will add some hoops.
I want to rename the name though validation not validation components Tiss angular style which we're
not using here.
So just validation is the name of the component without component.
Still execute a constant here where I assign that as 6 function.
And of course we'll receive some props here.
I already know that then I will import re-act from react as we need to do it.
Never forget this.
You will get errors about ways and I will export this as my default export in this file.
Now all that's left in this function is I need to return some JS X solver wise it's not a valid component
and therefore now it will return a paragraph where I will say text too short.
Of course it is not conditional at all right now.
Maybe already wrap this inside a div here.
So let's quickly adjust that.
So with that we get this component set up.
Let's now imported in the Baptist js file by adding a port at the top where I import validation with
a capital D validation from the validation folder and their D validation dot js file without the file
extension in the import.
I can now use it here below my input below the paragraph.
Maybe I'll add validation as a self-closing tag.
Now I also need to pass the text length as a prompt though.
So here I will simply add a prop and I'll name it input length.
The name is up to you.
I will add it like it is and simply pass this state.
User input length because it is a string it is an array therefore I can get the length of the input
and the validation dot Jr's fall.
I can then use it.
Now that will be part of the first task I should output text to short or text long enough.
The padding on the text length and you can choose any color if you want.
I'll go with 5 as I just here but that is totally optional.
So in there I'll add a second paragraph.
I already got the text too short.
One bad text long enough that's missing and I only want to output one of to two though.
Now there are a couple of ways you can do this.
The first way is to use a ternary expression as I showed you in the previous or in this module actually
in the previous lectures.
So here we could say if perhaps input length there will be input length Propp because that's what I
am passing here.
Input length and this will be the length of guess what my input.
So if that is let's say greater than five then I want to output text long enough otherwise.
I want to output text too short.
This should work with this turned every expression.
Make sure you save all the files and go back.
We all see text too short.
Now let me start typing.
We see Maxse million.
The next character it should switch text long enough and never remove a character it goes back to text
too short.
This works perfectly fine but what did I tell you about ternary expressions.
Use them with caution.
Now actually here it would be perfectly fine to use one.
This is a simple to understand GSX block.
Still let's use the batter approach.
Let's create a new variable which will name validation message where a by default will say text long
enough.
However I will then check if prop's input length is smaller or equal than 5.
So I'm simply lets do the other way around.
Then I will said validation message to text to short.
And of course I could not only assign a text to that I could assign the whole paragraph GSX both actually
works here.
I will go with the text to mix it up so down there I will then add my paragraph and inside the paragraph.
I will simply output validation message and this is heever text long enough or text too short.
And again the paragraph could be part of the variable too.
Now let's say if this change we should get the same behavior asked for and we do.
However this time here we do.
But a more elegant way by storing it in a separate variable hence making it a bit easier to read and
understand and maintain.
So this is their solution.
I recommend optionally Again don't use text here.
Create Agellius X element with the paragraph instead.
But this is definitely a good solution for tasks number of free.
Now let's move on and let's create another component the char component and stylesheet as the inline
box with for example the styles I suggest here.
So create a new folder in the source folder char and then there are char dotted genius file as before.
This doesn't need to have a state so we can simply create a functional component you're creating it
as a function.
So char is at six arrow function as we did it many times before.
We definitely needed to import to react as always because jazz X is just react create element never
forget it get this and then export char as the default in this file.
Now in there I now need to return some JSE X and I will actually return a div element wrapping everything.
Now for styling it we got two options.
We can set up a C S S file.
Import it.
Define a class in there and assign it here.
Or define inline Stahl's.
I'll go for the inline styles here but it's totally up to you.
So let me name this constant style.
The name doesn't matter though.
And now let me set up what I defined here so I will set the display to inline block.
I will set the padding to 16 pixels and I will set the margin to 6 and pixels.
I will set a border of 1 pixels solid and black.
What else that I have here.
Text align to center maybe to center everything nicely so text align to center.
This might not even be neater to be honest and it would work like this should be camel case because
we're in javascript.
Now I can assign this here dynamically with single quotation marks.
So now referring to that style constant.
Now we get.
Does component prepare it and we can also imported Indian file where I want to use it.
So import Chaar from slash char and their anti char chase file without the file extension.
But of course we're not using it yet.
We want to use it here.
We're getting warned that we're not using it actually.
We want to use it here to render a list for each character in the text.
A user entered.
So let's do that I will render this list below the validation here.
And I could now use this map.
Meffert right here.
But for the same reason I restructured the validation and pulled the logic outside of the J as X block
I returned.
I'll do it here.
Here I simply want to render a variable which I prepare prior to does return statement.
So there I will simply named is variable.
Char list for example and char list just can be a constant.
I'm never going to change it.
Chairlifts should reach out to my state to the user input and now call map to again map every element
in desirée into a new element.
Now desiré of course is just some text but that basically is an array of strings.
So here I will get my single char and you can of course also named as char whatever you want and I want
to return a j as x representation.
So I will return my char component and I will set a character and this name is also up to you.
Prop on it and pass the character I got here.
And again this could be named char whatever you like into it.
So no need to expect this character component Susie property inside my char component.
So there I will receive props and I will now simply output prop's character inside the return statement
there and then capture yes I simply create my list by Couldn't working desiré.
Keep in mind map doesn't touch the original array.
It simply gives you a new array which is stored in char list and you array of char components.
Now let's take that Jarre list constant and this is what I want to output between single Cauley braces
down there below the validation message.
Make sure all files are saved.
Now here we're facing the issue dead.
We can't use map of words that string are basically or kind of javascript arrays but not really to turn
them into javascript arrays.
All I have to do is call split on it though on the user input and pass an empty string as an argument.
This will basically split this into an array of strings after every character.
So now this should work if I enter test here.
You can see I get tests down there.
Now what you will see is that I get this key error.
So to fix this.
We should of course assign a key and here the thing with the key is a bit tricky because of that unique
ID which we don't really have in our example.
So what I will do is here on the chart.
I will indeed use the index though this is not optimal.
Better than no key though.
But not the best solution.
But here I get no other chance.
So let's use that second argument of the function inside the map Meffert the index with that if we now
reload the page.
This works without errors.
Now we're almost done.
Now we want to make sure that if I click one of these boxes we remove that character.
Now for that I'll add a new method in my app complainant's or name it.
Delete char handler and then I basically expect to get the index of the character I want to delete and
I want to execute this obviously whenever I click on one of these character boxes.
So let's flip this over multiple lines and then pass a property which I'll name collect where I then
want to execute does delete char handler past the index though and therefore execute this as an anonymous
E6 function using this alternate syntax of passing a reference.
Keep in mind this anonymous function is basically passed to clicked it's not executed immediately.
This would be the case if I had more parentheses at the end.
But here we simply pass a reference and then dysfunction will get executed when click property is fired
and then we call delete char handler.
So let's pass to collect property to char and there on the diff or at the on click handler and simply
pass a reference to prop's collect so that this will be executed and hence this function here will get
executed.
If I click a box and then we will get this index.
Now inside delete char handler I get this index.
I now want to update the user input which as you learned is only kind of a javascript string.
So what I would simply do here is.
I will first of all get my text by reaching out to this state.
User input and coaling split on an empty string just as we did before.
Before mapping.
Now I got an array of characters and there I now want to remove one with splice at the index position
and then only one character.
So this removes it from the array.
And now I want to create my update as text where I simply used the text.
This is an array of characters.
Keep that in mind which I now join again with an empty characters so with basically nothing but it can
words.
My array of characters into text into a string again and then I can call this set state and there I
can set user input equal to updated text.
This should actually do the trick.
Descaler should take my text updated and DUDAS for whichever char I clicked on.
Let me save this and let me enter a test text here.
Let me at.
Click this year it's removed and it's also removed from the input and to text the output here and then
if I remove a lot of content from there actually are validation also comes to too short again so everything
is dynamic.
Everything works here as it should with conditional rendering and with outputting lists.